<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sinners inditement. By William Ward minister of the word of God</title>
            <author>Ward, William, d. 1632.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A14766</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854852</idno>
  <idno type="VID">20306</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240927455</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 25062</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S119645</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99854852e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A14766)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20306)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1534:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sinners inditement. By William Ward minister of the word of God</title>
                  <author>Ward, William, d. 1632.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 151, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By W. White, for Tho. Pauier in Iuie lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1615.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Amanda Flynn</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20306:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:20306:1"/>
            <fw>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>decorative border</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </fw>
            <p>A SINNERS INDITEMENT. By WILLIAM WARD Minister of the word of GOD.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>Woodcut printer's device (not in McKerrow).</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Imprinted at London by W. White, for Tho. Pauier in Iuielane. 1615.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraph">
            <pb facs="tcp:20306:2"/>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Leuit.</hi> 26. <hi>vers.</hi> 3, 4, 18, 19, 20.</bibl>
               <p n="3">3 If you walke in mine Ordinances, and keepe my Commandements, and doe them.</p>
               <p n="4">4 I will send you raine in due season, &amp; the Land shall yeeld her increase, and the Trees of the Field shall giue their fruite.</p>
               <p n="18">18 And if you will not for these things obey me, then will I punish you seuen times more, according to your sinnes.</p>
               <p n="19">19 And I will breake the pride of your power, and I will make your Heauen as Iron, and your Earth as Brasse.</p>
               <p n="20">20 And your strength shall be spent in vaine; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther shall your Land giue her increase, neither shall the Trees of the land giue their fruite.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:20306:2"/>
            <head>To the right Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shipfull &amp; worthy Patron of good Learning, S. <hi>Henrie Pierre-pont</hi> Knight, <hi>one of his Maiesties Iustices of the</hi> Peace in the County of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> W. W. <hi>Minister of the word of God</hi> at <hi>Prestvvold</hi> in <hi>Leicestershire,</hi> wish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the rich blessinges of God, externall, internall, and eternall.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>IR: When the Tabernacle was builded by <hi>Moses</hi> for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship and seruice of God, <hi>Euery one brought such as they</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 25. 3, 4, 5, 6, 7.</note>
               <hi>had,</hi> some more, some lesse; some better, some worse; and all was necessarie for the Worke: Euen so, for the building of Gods Church, euery one should bring such as they haue, according to the abilitie which the Lord of the House hath giuen vnto them, to profit with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; and therefore I (though the least of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stles children) doe hold my selfe bound to dooe something; for <hi>Pauls Woe</hi> will light vpon mee, <hi>If I preach not the Ghospell;</hi> assuring my <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 16.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:20306:3"/> selfe, that the Maister of the Worke will accept of my poore seruice, as our Sauiour Christ did <hi>of the Widdows Mite cast into the treasury.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 21. 2. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>I know very well (right Worshipfull) that some are so puffed vp, that they scorne, so much as to <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 18. 19.</note> affoord their eyes to read, or their eares to heare the writings or words of any, but onely such as are excellent, and eminent for Learning and Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence: notwithstanding experience teacheth, that men of meaner Giftes, and (for their Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning) not worthy to carry the Bookes of the Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned after them, doe sometimes speake as effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to the Consciences of the Country people, as those whom the Lord hath graced and intrusted with many Talents: Neither doe I doubt, but as the Apostle speakes of Almes, so in this action. <hi>If first there be a willing minde, it is accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8. 1.</note>
               <hi>according to that a man hath, and not according to that he hath not.</hi> Now the speciall cause of my presuming to present this poore Paper-gift into your hands, arising not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly out of that christian and reciprocall loue that I beare to your person, because you fauour Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning &amp; loue them that are Learned (so that, as it was once truly said of the house of that renow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and blessed Saint of God <hi>Henrie</hi> late Earle of <hi>Huntington</hi> I President of <hi>Yorke,</hi> that it was in his time a Sanctuarie for the Cleargie) so
<pb facs="tcp:20306:3"/> it may as truly be reported, and passe for currant, that your House (most noble Knight) I speake be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, without flatterie, is not onely a Nursery for poore Schollers, but also a refuge and recep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacle for all faythfull, painefull, and godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters, and your selfe a Sword and Shield, to your <hi>posse,</hi> for them: But also for the many and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deserued kindnesses and fauours, which (by the blessing of God) I haue found flowing from you vpon so small acquaintance; and that your meere bountie, without the least desert of mine: which if I should burie in obliuion, or drowne in the riuer <hi>Lethe,</hi> I might iustly be condemned of ingrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude with the nine <hi>Leapers,</hi> and accounted (as <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk</hi> 17. 17.</note>
               <hi>Ouid</hi> speakes) <hi>Telluris inutile pondus,</hi> not worthy to inioy the common ayre, because, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratum si dixeris, omnia dixisti.</hi> When I was driuen to a <hi>non plus</hi> what course to take for the preferring of that young Impe, my Sonne, to the Vniuersitie, it pleased God (who worketh all for the best to those that are his) to make you the blessed instrument of no lesse comfort vnto mee, then the Angel was to <hi>Hagar</hi> in the Wildernesse. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 21. 15. 16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And when I heard that it pleased you to take a good liking of him, being a Scholler neere to your house in <hi>Nottingham,</hi> and vpon my first acquaintance with you, commended him, not only to mee, but also to that good Knight S. <hi>William</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:20306:4"/>
               <hi>Skip with,</hi> who was his Godfather, and of whom the Country hath now a great losse, I was raui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed with no lesse ioy, then was old <hi>Iacob,</hi> when <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 45, 27</note> he saw the Chariots which his Sonne <hi>Ioseph</hi> had sent to carry him into <hi>Egipt.</hi> For what greater earthly comfort to a Father, then to see and heare his Child accepted of, and commended, by those that are wise, learned, and in place of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, and authoritie. To knit vp all in a word, my especiall desire is, that it may please you to accept of my simple seruice herein, and to take this poore offering with like affection as that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>Artaxerxes</hi> did the Water which a poore man brought him in the hollow of his hand: which fauour, if I may find at your Worships hands (as I cannot doubt but it will easily be found) then shall I account my selfe thrice happy. Thus, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seeching the Almighty to multiply his blessinges vpon you, and yours, with increase of Worship in this life, &amp; perfection of Honour and Glory in the life to come, I commit you to the protectiō of him, who neuer leaueth his.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Prestwold.</hi>
                  <date>Iune. 20. 1612.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Worships in Christ to be commanded during life,</hi> William Ward.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20306:4"/>
            <head>A SINNERS INDITEMENT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Hosea. 4. vese. 1, 2, 3.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p n="1">1. <hi>Heare the word of the Lord ye children of</hi> Israel, <hi>for the Lord hath a Controuersie with the Inhabitants of the Land, because there is no truth, nor mercie, nor knowledge of God in the Land.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>By Swearing, and Lying, and Killing, and Stealing, and Whoaring, they breake out, and Blood toucheth Blood.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Therefore shall the Land mourne, and euery one that dwels therein shall be cut off, with the Beastes of the Field, and with the Foules of the Heauen: and also the Fishes of the Sea, shall be taken away.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Lord by the Ministerie and seruice of the Prophet <hi>Hosea,</hi> la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured the space of Threescore and ten yeares, to draw the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to repentance; but they notwithstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding grew worse and worse, so that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:20306:5"/> Mercies, nor Iudgments, threatnings, nor promises, could winne them, nor worke vpon them: Therefore the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Hosea</hi> giueth them ouer, and leaueth them to Gods Iudgements. Of this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture there are foure parts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. First, an Inditement or Citation of the people to appeare before the Lord: <hi>Heare the Word. &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. The matter of the Inditement or Citation, in these words: <hi>The Lord hath a Controuersie. &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. The cause of the Controuersie: <hi>Sinne.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. Iudgement against them: <hi>Therefore the Land shall mourne. &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the Inditement, or Citation.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. He stirreth vp the people to atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>Heare.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Hee setteth downe three Reasons wherefore they should be attentiue.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <item>1. Because it is the Word of the Lord, that they should heare.</item>
               <item>2. Because they were the people of <hi>Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> that should heare it.</item>
               <item>3. Because the Word belonged vnto them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>In the matter of the Inditement hee sheweth,</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:20306:5"/>
               <item>1. Who is the Plaintiffe, viz. <hi>The Lord.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Who are the Defendants: <hi>The Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Land.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The cause of the Inditement or Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie, is Sinne: which is of two sorts;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Sinnes of Omission, for duties omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</item>
               <item>2. Sinnes of Commission, for wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse committed.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Their Sinnes are amplified by a me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphore of breaking out, as a violent streame.</p>
            <p>Lastly, in the third verse hee proceedes to Iudgement, which is first set downe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the people, in these words: <hi>The Land shall mourne, and euery one that dwelles therein shall be cut off.</hi> Secondly, more amply extending to the dumbe creatures, in these words: <hi>With the Beasts of the field, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs first consider of the coherence of the scripture with that which went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>In the last verse of the former chapter, the Lord by his Prophet speaketh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable things vnto them; now in these words, he threatneth them.</p>
            <p>The Ministers of the word may hence learne of the Prophet <hi>Hosea, To mingle Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:20306:6"/>
               <hi>with Threatnings, and Mercy with Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay. 8. 21. 22.</note> the Lord threatneth the pleople with Iudgments, but he comforteth them <hi>with the promise of the Messiah.</hi> Christ de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth <note place="margin">Eay. 9.</note> Curses, <hi>Woe to thee Corazin; Woe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 11. 21. 28.</note>
               <hi>to thee Bethsaida:</hi> but verse 28. hee giueth comfort; <hi>Come vnto mee all yee that trauaile and be heauie loaden, and I will refresh you:</hi> yea, the very names of some of Christes Apostles, doe teach thus much. Some are called <hi>Boanerges, Sonnes of Thunder:</hi> but <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas</hi> was the sonne of Comfort. <hi>My song</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mark. 3. 17.</note>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 101. 1.</note> (saith <hi>Dauid) shall be of Mercie and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reason hereof is this, because Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie without Iudgement, leads men to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sumption; and Iudgement without Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, driues men to desperation: therefore Promises and Threatnings in a Cristian proportion, according to the occasion, should be mingled togeather.</p>
            <p>This should teach the Ministers to be discreete, and to preach Mercy to whom Mercy appertaineth; and Iudgements to them that are hardned. We should (as good Stewards) giue euery one that por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which is fit for him: When wee see sinne abound, and the hand of God stret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:20306:6"/> foorth to punish the people, wee should not then preach Peace vnto them, but tell them, and tell them againe, that <hi>The Lord hath a controuersie with them;</hi> and <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they repent, they shall all perish.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, whereas the Ministers ought to preach to the people both Iudgements and Mercy, they also (the people I meane) should vse Wisedome in applying them both, to themselues. The impenitent sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, may not promise the Mercy of God to himselfe which he hath nothing to doe withall; neither should the penitent sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner trouble himselfe with Gods Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p>If thou doest truely repent thee of thy sinnes, then Gods Mercy belongeth to thee, thou mayest say truely, thou hast no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to doe with Gods Iudgements: But if thou hearest the Iudgements of God pronounced against those sinnes whereof thou art guiltie, and doest not apply those Iudgements to thy selfe, but departest in thy sinnes, and blessest thy selfe in them with an hardned heart, the promise of Gods Mercy belongs not to thee; <hi>It is the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 29. 18</note>
               <hi>Childrens Bread, It is not for such Swine and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math 15 26</note>
               <hi>Dogs as thou art.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:20306:7"/>
            <p>Thirdly, euery one may heere examine himselfe, what good either the Promises or Threatnings of God (so often denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the Ministers for sinne) haue done, or what they haue preuayled with vs? Are we not (for the most part) like the people of <hi>Israel,</hi> whom neither the Promises nor Threatnings of God could moue to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and amendment? And though the Lord afflict vs from top to toe with new afflictions, as with Plague, Pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, strange Sicknesses, and vnseasona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Weather; yet we fall away daily, and grow worse &amp; worse. We are those Fooles whom <hi>Salomon</hi> speaketh of: <hi>Though the Lord doe bray vs (as it were in a Morter) with</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 27. 22.</note>
               <hi>one Affliction after another, yet are we sowed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to Wickednesse, that leaue it we cannot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs euery one then search his owne Conscience, and see what good these Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions haue wrought vpon vs. Happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, some may promise amendment of life, like <hi>Pharao,</hi> while Gods hand was heauy vpon him; but when the storme is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blowen, then they fall againe to their old by as, as bad as euer they were. What then should the Lord doe with such a people as we are, whom neither his Mercies, nor
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:20306:7"/> Iudgements, can worke vpon? What should a Carpender doe with a peece of Wood that will serue to no vse in the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, but cast it into the fire? The Law of God by <hi>Moses</hi> was, that, <hi>If any man had a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 21. 18.</note>
               <hi>Sonne that were stubborne and disobedient, which would not harken vnto the voyce of his Father, nor the voyce of his Mother; and though they chastened him, he would not obey them, then his Father and Mother should take him, and bring him out vnto the Elders of his Citie, and vnto the Gate of the place where he dwelt, and should say to the Elders of his Citie, This our Sonne is stubborne and disobedient, and hee will not obey our admonition: hee is a Royotor, and a Drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard. Then all the men of his Citie shall stone him with Stones vnto death.</hi> The Lord God is our Father, we are his Children; if wee be stubborne against our heauenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, so as neither his Mercies nor Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments deliuered by his Ministers, are of vs regarded, what shall the Lord doe with vs, but cast vs off to destruction?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they are heere reprooued which can be contented to heare Gods Promises, but not his Iudgements. <hi>Felix</hi> could not abide to heare of Iudgement. <note place="margin">Act. 24. 26.</note>
               <hi>Balthaser</hi> seeing Gods Iudgements, could <note place="margin">Dan. 5. 6.</note>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:20306:8"/> not hold a ioynt of him still. And this is that which maketh the Ministers of the Gospell often to be hated amongst bad men; Oh (say they) he hath nothing but Iudgements in his mouth. So was the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micha</hi> hated of wicked King <hi>Ahab: I hate him, I neuer heard good from him. Ahab</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kin. 22. 8.</note> was a bad man, and therefore the Prophet of God could not prophesie good of him. We are hated of bad men, because we rip vp their sinnes. Shall we see God haue a controuersie with you for your sinnes, and we flatter you in your sinnes? Rather acknowledge it a blessing of God, that you haue such Ministers as can and dare tell you that the Lord hath a Controuersie with you. And thus much concerning the coherence of this Scripture, with that which went before in the last verse of the former Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Heare the Word of the Lord.</hi> The Prophet stirreth them vp to heare the Word. When we come to teach, we should stirre vp the people to attention. As God in giuing the Law obserued this stile: <hi>Heare the Word of the Lord.</hi> So did also the Prophets. <hi>Heare</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 5. 1.</note>
               <hi>the Word of the Lord. Hearken to the Law of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay. 1. 10. Iere. 13. 25.</note>
               <hi>our God. Heare, and giue eare, be not proud; for</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:20306:8"/>
               <hi>the Lord hath spoken it.</hi> And Christ saith, <hi>He that hath eares to heare, let him heare. Let him</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 13. 9.</note>
               <hi>that hath an eare, heare what the Spirit speaketh</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 2. 29.</note>
               <hi>to the Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ministers should stirre vp the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to attention: First, for their owne good, and secondly for the good of the people. It is a chearefull thing to see the people attentiue. When Christ preached, <hi>The eyes of all that were in the Sinagogue, were</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 4. 20.</note>
               <hi>fastned on him.</hi> But when the Minister seeth the hearers not attentiue, it is a cooling to his spirit. When the people would not heare the Prophet <hi>Esay,</hi> he speaks to <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and Earth.</hi> Secondly, we should stirre <note place="margin">Esay 12.</note> vp the people to attention for their owne good, because they shal reape no prophet, vnlesse they be attentiue. Dull we are and drowsie by nature, and therefore had need to be stirred vp to attention.</p>
            <p>Let vs then make Conscience to heare the Word of the Lord attentiuely. If you feele dulnesse, stirre vp your selues. Be swift to heare. God hath giuen vs eares not to the end that wee should take de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to heare filthy thinges, nor to heare pick-thankes, and make-bates, which for a peece of Bread and Cheese, or a pot of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:20306:9"/> Beere to carry lyes &amp; tales to set variance among neighbours; but that wee should incline our eares to heare what the Lord speaketh to vs by his Ministers, whether Promises, or Threatnings: neither is it enough to lend him our eares, but we must heare with attention, feare, reuerence, and care to practise that which we heare.</p>
            <p>The first reason wherefore the Prophet stirreth them vp to attention is, because it is the word of the Lord which he would haue them to heare. We should heare the Word of the Lord attentiuely, because it is the Word of the Lord, for the Words sake, <hi>Not as the Word of Men, but as it is in deed the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Thes. 2. 13.</note>
               <hi>Word of God.</hi> Wee speake from God; God speaketh to his Church by his Ministers: <hi>Hee spake by the mouth of his holy Prophets.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 1. 70.</note> And his Apostles: <hi>It is not yee that speake</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>but the spirit of your Father</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 10. 20.</note>
               <hi>which speaketh in you.</hi> Though the tongue of a mortall man wagge, the matter is from Gods owne mouth: and though sinfull mans lippes mooue, yet it is the Word of the liuing God. Wee must heare the Word with attention, for the Words sake; <hi>Because it is the Word of the Lord.</hi> This serueth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prooue <note place="margin">Gall. 1. 10.</note> them which heare the Word, not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:20306:9"/> for the words sake, because it is the word of the Lord, but for his sake that spake it. If they like of the Preacher, why then they like of the Sermon, then he spake well. If he be a Kinsman, a Friend, a man of Authoritie, or a Stranger, he beareth away (for the most part) the applause of the people: But if they affect not the Preacher, then they like not of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. If he be a poore man, then he is of lesse account; hee is but a poore man, no matter what hee speaks. But Gods children should not respect the man that speaketh, but heare him with reuerence, and accept the Word for the Wordes sake, because it is the Word of the Lord.</p>
            <p>The second reason wherefore he stir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them vp to heare the Word of the Lord is, because they were the Children of <hi>Israel.</hi> We should heare the Word of the Lord with attention, and obedience, because we are the Inheritaunce of God. <hi>Heare my Doctrine, O my people. Wee are of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal 78. 1.</note>
               <hi>God; hee that knoweth God, heareth vs: hee</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 4. 6.</note>
               <hi>that is not of God, heareth vs not.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet then calling them the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> putteth them in minde as Christ doth the <hi>Jewes. If you were Abrahams chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 39.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:20306:10"/>
               <hi>ye would doe the workes of Abraham.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 39.</note> This, &amp; such like high titles to be called, <hi>The children of Israel, Abrahams children, children of God, Christans &amp;c.</hi> should in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage vs to heare the word attentiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to beleiue it, and yeild obedience to it.</p>
            <p>Hence they are iustly to be reproued, which would be called the people of God, <hi>Gods children, Christians &amp;c.</hi> And yet make no conscience to heare the word of the Lord, much lesse to practise it in their life, and conuersation; If thou haue no care to heare the word of God with attention, and to make practise of it in the course of thy life, thou art not of God: <hi>He that is of God, heareth Gods words: ye therefore heare them not, because ye</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 47.</note>
               <hi>are not of God.</hi> I am of God therfore I will heare Gods word, and will labour to liue according to his word. I am a Christian, therefore I will frame my selfe to liue the life of a christian, and follow the steps of my Maister Christ, of whom I am called a Christian. We should heare the word of the Lord with attention, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, because wee are Christians.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that he might the better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade them to attention, he tels them,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:20306:10"/> it belongs to them: The iudgement, the quarrell, the Inditment is against you, therefore looke you to it, ye Children of <hi>Israell.</hi> When the Lord by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets or ministers doth deliuer his word to the people, what is spoken before them, is spoken to them, whether com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort or threatnings. What the Minister speakes before the people, is spoken to the people, and ment of them. This is prooued by the end of sending the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: the Lord send them not to smite the Ayer, but the Heart, not to speake to the absent, but to the present. They that heare the word of God should apply it to their consciences, for their amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, euery one saying to himselfe, this is spoken of me, this is ment of me; now the spirit of God knockes at the doore of my heart, if now I open and receaue such a blessed guest, happy am I that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer I was borne: but if now I omit this oportunite, who can tel whether the like occasion will euer be offered to me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. But the common sort of people cannot abide this; Nay if they doe but coniecture that what is spoken touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, then they spight and enuie
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:20306:11"/> the speaker, or else post it ouer as spoken to others; notwithstanding Gods child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren doe vnbowell their hearts, and pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sesse their souls with euery sentence that the minister speaketh; they haue a feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of their sinnes, &amp; therfore perswade themselues that Gods iudgments belong to them, as did <hi>Dauid,</hi> when the Angell streched out his hand towards Ierusalem to destroye it, <hi>Dauid</hi> sayd, <hi>It is I that haue</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 24. 17.</note>
               <hi>sinned, it is I that haue done wickedly.</hi> We must not post ouer Gods iudgments as done to others, we must account the sin reprehended to be ours, &amp; Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to belong to vs, our sinnes haue deserued worse, if iudgement should be extended.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as you must apply what is spoken to your selues for your amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: so wee that are the ministers of the word, may heere learne of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Hosea</hi> not to balke the people with whom wee haue to deale, nor to flatter them in their sins, but to speake to their consciences as the prophet here doth, <hi>Heare the word of the Lord yee children of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell.</hi> We must apply our words to the people that stand before vs, that they
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:20306:11"/> may know it belongs to them. While <hi>Nathan</hi> spake by parables, <hi>Dauid</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stood him not, till it was applyed to his Conscience. Except we make applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Doctrine, and the people take it as spoken to their good, we may aswel speake to the Pillars of the Church, as to the people in the Church: for as a Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster lapt vp in a Box and put into a mans Pocket, healeth not his so are, vnlesse it be applyed to it: so the Word of God cureth not the Maladies of our Soules, except it be clapt close to the corrupted Conscience. And thus much concerning the Inditement.</p>
            <p>Now followeth the matter of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement. <hi>The Lord hath a Controuersie with the Inhabitants of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two things herein I note (as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sayd.)</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Who is the Plaintiffe, viz. <hi>The Lord.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 Who are the Defendants. <hi>The Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the land.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Prophet had cryed out against their sinnes many yeares, and could doe no good: hee saw they were vncurable and therefore hee puts the matter into
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:20306:12"/> Gods hands.</p>
            <p>When the people are so hardned in their sinnes that the Preachers of the word can doe no good on them, they may spend their voyce, their bodies, their wittes, and all in vaine: then the Lord will plead his owne cause. When <hi>Noah</hi> could doe no good among the people, God then tooke the matter into his owne hand. <hi>My spirit</hi> (sayth he) <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 3.</note>
               <hi>shall not alway striue with man, because he is but flesh. Lot</hi> laboured in the Lords businesse among the Sodomites, in cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them to repentance, but when <hi>Lot</hi> could doe no good, God pleaded his owne cause among them, with Fire and Brimstone. God in mercy hath called vs many yeeres to repentance by his Ministers, but (alas) you see many are so hardned in their sinnes, that wee can doe no good with them, and therefore the Lord beginneth to take the matter into his owne hand; and to plead his owne cause, by plague and pestilence, and by sending such vnseasonable wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther amongst vs.</p>
            <p>This serueth to terrifie the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of the word, who hauing so long
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:20306:12"/> despised the voyce of Gods Ministers, are to looke for nothing but the thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring voyce of God from heauen, and the heauy sound of his Iudgements.</p>
            <p>The Lord hath a controuersie with the Inhabitants of the Land. God is the plantiffe, hee will trie an action with the Inhabitants of the Land, and he will proceed in Iudgement with good aduise.</p>
            <p>God punisheth not but with diligent search of the matter. <hi>I will goe downe now</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 21.</note>
               <hi>and see whether they haue done altogeather according to that cry which is come vnto mee; if not, that I may know.</hi> What needs all this? what needs God to goe downe and see? God fulfils all things. This is spoken to our capacity, he proceeds to Iudgment iustly, he hath cause to doe it, he is iust in all his wayes, and holy in all his workes, yea, he is Iustice it selfe. He is iust in executing vengeance on the vniust, he spared not the Angels, nor his owne people the Iewes, nor Ierusalem his owne Citty, hee hath not spared his dearest children, as <hi>Dauid,</hi> and others, but as they fell, so they felt the heauy hand of his Iudgements
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:20306:13"/> against them.</p>
            <p>When God is Plaintiffe, and hath a Controuersie with any people, hee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds in Iudgement with such Iustice, that the very Consciences of the Defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants cannot but confesse that they are iustly punished. God is not like the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull Rich men of this World, who when they are Plaintiffes, and haue a Controuersie with any inferior to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues in wealth and power, for the most part, they labour to weary them out with vniust sutes, so as the poore man must ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther loose his right, or spend that porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that God hath giuen him, in maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his right, to the vtter vndoing, and impouerishing of himselfe his wife and children for euer.</p>
            <p>God proceedes against the Wicked iustly. When men haue greatest mercies &amp; blessings bestowed on them, &amp; abuse them, God in iustice, executes greatest punishments on them. <hi>The Serpent was the most wise and subtile Beast;</hi> but when hee abused his Wisedome, hee was accursed <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 1.</note> aboue all other Beastes. The place of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> was a fruitefull Valley, compared to the Garden <hi>Eden;</hi> but when they abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed <note place="margin">Gen. 13. 10.</note>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:20306:13"/> the blessings of God, where before it was a most pleasant place, and fruitfull, God sent such punishment vpon them, that it became a place most odious, no Beast, Foule, nor Fish is able to abide in it. <hi>Ierusalem</hi> was the place of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship, and the <hi>Iewes</hi> Gods people: But when they abused Gods blessings, they were destroyed, and their Temple made a heape of Stones. <hi>Diues</hi> abused Gods guifts in delicate Fare; but at last, hee would haue been glad of <hi>A drop of Water</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 24.</note>
               <hi>to coole his tongue.</hi> The prodigall Sonne, who want only wasted his Childes part with Drunkennesse, Rioting, &amp; Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, (like our English Spend-thriftes) was in the end glad to be a Swine-heard, <note place="margin">Luk. 15. 16.</note> and fare as the Swine fed.</p>
            <p>This serueth for our instruction. God hath dealt more mercifully with vs, then with any Nation vnder heauen; we haue had health, peace, and plenty: but wee haue abused them all, and therefore it is a iust thing with God, to proceed as Plaintiffe against vs: neither doth he vs any wrong, if he turne our Health into Sicknesse, our Peace into Warre, and our Plenty into Want; our sinnes haue iusty
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:20306:14"/> deserued it. I report mee to your owne knowledge, how plentifully God hath blessed vs with the Fruites of the Earth from yeare to yeare; so that the Vallies stand so thicke with Corne, that they laugh and sing, as <hi>Dauid</hi> speakes. But <note place="margin">Psal. 65. 14.</note> (alas) how doe wee abuse, and imbezell those rich blessings of God?</p>
            <p>And therefore God may in iustice deale with vs, as hee did with the Noble man in the famine of <hi>Samaria;</hi> Who <note place="margin">2. Reg. 7. 2.</note> when <hi>Elisha</hi> prophesied that within foure and twenty howes, their Famine should be relieued with Plenty; He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered: <hi>Though the Lord would make Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes in the Heauen, could this thing come to passe? Elisha</hi> replied: <hi>Behold, thou shalt see it with thine eyes, but thou shalt not eate thereof.</hi> So (I say) God may iustly deale with vs, for abusing the Fruites of the Earth: Wee see a plentifull Haruest on the Ground, but God may (for our sinnes) so continue this vnseasonable Weather, that, though we see great plenty, and are readie to reape it, yet except God in mercie▪ looke vpon vs, wee shall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eate it, nor inioy it. GOD may iustly deale with vs, as with the <hi>Israelites,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:20306:14"/> the Lord gaue them aboundaunce of <note place="margin">Num. 11. 31. 32.</note> Quailes, but withall he sent Leanenesse into their Soules; and while the Meate was yet in their mouthes, the heauie Wrath of GOD fell vpon them. So <note place="margin">Psal. 78. 31.</note> though God haue sent aboundance of Corne vpon the ground, hee may iustly (for our abusing of it to wantonnesse and excesse) so curse it vnto vs, that it may neuer doe vs good; and it is an heauie Iudgement of God, when (for our sinne) hee turneth his Blessinges into Curses vnto vs: And executeth Vengeance in those thinges that should <note place="margin">Mal. 2. 2.</note> bee Blessinges vnto vs. The Raine is a Blessing of GOD, which hee promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth to his Seruants, to make the earth <note place="margin">Leuit. 26. 4.</note> fruitfull. Among other Blessinges to his people, the Lord promiseth to open <hi>The Heauen, to giue them Raine in due sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 28. 12.</note> for without Raine, the Earth would be altogeather barren, and vnfruitfull: But how heauie a Iudgement is it, when God, because of sinne, turneth his Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>singes into Curses, and destroyeth the Fruites of the earth, with immoderate and too much Raine.</p>
            <p>This should teach vs to iustifie God
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:20306:15"/> in his iudgments, he neuer punisheth but iustly, and our consciences witnesse against vs, that we haue deserued worse: let vs not thinke with <hi>Iob,</hi> that our pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment is greater then our sin, though Gods hand in punishing bee heauy and his iudgments great and greeuous, he hath cause to doe it, hee is iust in all his wayes, and holy in all his workes.</p>
            <p>And seeing God can turne his bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings into curses, as a iust reward of our sinne, let vs acknowledge the power of God, and let vs hate sinne, which is cause of his Iudgements vpon vs. And if wee would haue his heauy hand remooued, wee must first remooue our sinnes: if wee continue in our wickednesse, and heape sinne vpon sinne, Gods hand wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be stretched out still, to heape Iudgment vpon Iudgment, and prosecute his suite against vs, till he haue destroyed vs: but if wee would haue God let his sute fall, and be at one with vs, we must turne euery one from his euill way, and then God will turne his iudgments from vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord hath a controuersie with the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Land.</hi> If the Lord haue a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie or quarrell with a Kingdome,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:20306:15"/> Country, or people, <hi>Who is able to stand in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 90. 9.</note>
               <hi>his sight when hee is angry?</hi> As, <hi>If the Lord be</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 21.</note>
               <hi>on our side, who can be against vs:</hi> So if the Lord haue a controuersie with vs, what creature shalbe able to stand for vs? Nay, if God be against vs, nothing in heauen, nor in earth can do vs any good, but will be ready to execute Gods ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance on vs. Looke how many crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures God hath in heauen, earth, and hell, so many meanes he hath to punish vs, or vtterly to destroy vs, if because of our sinnes he bee at oddes with vs, or haue a quarrell against vs. He can as easily send strange plagues and diseases among vs, as in former times hee hath done: hee can arme all his creatures against vs, Hee is the Lord of Hostes. He hath the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in heauen, men, and all creatures on the earth, and all the diuels in hell, at his <note place="margin">Ecclsias. 39. 29.</note> beck to punish and destroy. He hath the Sunne, Moone, Starres, Fire, Water, Ayre, Earth, to take vengeance on vs for our sinnes. In <hi>Noah</hi> his time, the droppes <note place="margin">Gen. 7. 17.</note> of Raine were Gods Armie, to destroy the first World. Fire was his Host to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi> Haile-stones, <note place="margin">Gen. 19. 24. Iob 38. 22. 23. Ios. 10. 11.</note> and Snow. Frogges, Flies, Lice, and all
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:20306:16"/> creatures are Gods army, and when God sends them foorth to punish, though in their kind they be as weake as Water (as wee say in the Prouerbe) yet God can make them strong, and able to destroy whole Countries and Kingdomes. God hauing a Controuersie with <hi>Pharao,</hi> and the <hi>Egiptians: Exo.</hi> 8. 6. 16. He sent not out Legions of Angels against them, neither did hee leauy an Army of Footmen and Horsemen against them; but he sent out an Host of Flies, Frogs, &amp; other his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kest creatures, and these were confessed to be the Finger of God, and were able to bring downe all the pride of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 8. 19.</note> and the <hi>Egiptians.</hi> When God had a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie with the <hi>Philistins,</hi> because they <note place="margin">1. Sam. 6. 5.</note> had destroyed the people, taken away the Arke of God, and blessed their Idols for the victory, the Lord sent a multitude of Mice to destroy their Land. So also, when the Lord had a quarrell with King <hi>Herod,</hi> because he stretched out his hand to vex certaine of the Church, had killed <hi>Iames,</hi> and put <hi>Peter</hi> in prison, God sent an Angell to smite him; <hi>He was eaten with</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 12. 1, 2, 3.</note>
               <hi>Wormes, and gaue vp the ghost.</hi> I read of one <hi>Hatto,</hi> sometimes Bishop of <hi>Mentz</hi> in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:20306:16"/>
               <hi>Germany,</hi> who in time of dearth, hauing great store of Corne, would not bring it foorth for the reliefe of the people, but suffered the Rattes to eate it; wherefore God in his vengeance, raised vp such a multitude of Rats about him, that they made him to flee from house to house, to saue his life; and at last, hauing a strong Tower in the middest of the great Riuer <hi>Rhene,</hi> which yet remaineth to this day, hee fledde thither, as to his <hi>Ʋltimum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugium;</hi> But the Rattes, like Gods vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant Armie, swamme after him thyther also, and there deuoured him: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is called the <hi>Rattes Tower</hi> to this day. Let vs take heed how we prouoke God to wrath, or cause him to be at va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riance with vs because of our sinnes, seeing he hath all Creatures at his becke to punish vs; and can arme the weakest of them with strength, to execute his wrath vpō vs; he can scatter vs as Chaffe before the winde, he can tread vs vnder foote, as Clay in the Streetes: hee can make the smalest Vermine to be our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, and the least Dust to be our death. The murther of <hi>Habel</hi> lay so hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy vpon the conscience of <hi>Kain,</hi> that it <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 14.</note>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:20306:17"/> made him stand in feare of euery Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that met him, or ouertooke him: If then wee would be at peace with the Creatures, and find that peace in our selues which passeth all vnderstanding, we must first labour to be at peace with God, let him haue no controuersie with vs, for sinne; and then wee need not to stand in feare of the Creatures: If God be on our side, who can be against vs? <hi>He will make the Stones of the field to be at a league with vs, and the Beasts of the field to be</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 5. 23.</note>
               <hi>at peace with vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord hath a Controuersie with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of the Land.</hi> The people had long abused the patience, and long suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of God; and after many admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and warninges giuen, would not be reclaymed, and therefore the Lord now lets them vnderstand by the Prophet, that he will beare with them no longer, but will try an action with thē himselfe.</p>
            <p>It is the manner of God, to threaten and giue warning, before he punish, that men may haue time to aduise themselues to repent, or else to stand vnexcusable before God: for though Gods Bow be alwayes bent, and his Arrowes ready
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:20306:17"/> within his quiuer to shoot; yet seldome smites he, but first giueth warning pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his wrath. God gaue warning to the wicked world, in the dayes of <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 9.</note>
               <hi>Noah,</hi> an hundred and twenty yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee executed vengeance on them. God bare with the abhomination of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 15. 13.</note> foure hundred yeare. God suffered the <hi>Israelits</hi> in their sinnes, fourty yeares. Vertues were wrought in <hi>Corazin</hi> and <note place="margin">Psal. 95. 10.</note>
               <hi>Bethsaida</hi> before the Woe fell on them. Hee that had the Figtree in his Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, <note place="margin">Math. 11. 21.</note> came yeere by yeare, the space of three yeares, &amp; sought fruite theron, and found none; then he said, Cut it downe, <note place="margin">Luk. 13. 6. 7. 8 9.</note> why keepeth it the ground barren, but vpon intreaty he suffered it to grow the fourth yeare, and he caused it to be dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged and manured, still expecting fruite. Let vs take heede we abuse not the long suffering of God; hath the Lord pleaded his cause from heauen amongst vs, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing vs warning of his wrath? Hath he testified it by dearth, feareful thundrings from Heauen, vnseasonable Weather, Plague and Pestilence in blood. Doth he yet send vs warning peeces of his wrath, and correct vs in mercie? Let vs not
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:20306:18"/> abuse his long-suffering any longer, let his mercifull patience lead vs to repentaunce, and not harden vs in our sinnes. Hee is slow to wrath, hee <note place="margin">Rom. 2. 4.</note> would not the death of sinners, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that they should repent and liue. Hee laboureth to wooe vs, and winne vs to repentance: <hi>Why will yee die, O yee house of Israel, seeing I haue no pleasure in the death</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 33. 11.</note>
               <hi>of him that dieth,</hi> (saith the Lord.) Let vs not then (I say againe) abuse his long suffering any further, because we know not whether he will yet giue vs the space of one yeare, one moneth, or so much as one day more for Repentance. Examine thy selfe, in the feare of God, I aduise thee. Hast thou liued an euill life? Haue thy sinnes set God at variance with thee, and caused him to enter sute against thee? Hath God notwithstanding forborne and suffered thee many yeares in thy sinnes? thinke not therfore that God regards not thy sinnes because he doth not presently punish thee; he is slow to wrath, and prone to mercy. How many old hipocrits, old whore-mongers and whores, old drunkards, vsurers, blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous swearers, &amp;c. are at this day in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:20306:18"/> this Christian world growing old in sin, as they wax aged in yeares, whom God hath forborne, and suffered a long time in their abhominations. God dealeth not alwayes with whore-mongers, as with <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbie;</hi> Whom he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroyed, euen as they were committing <note place="margin">Num. 25. 8.</note> their filthynesse. Nor with hipocrits, as with <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> vpon whom hee inflicted sodaine destruction: and <note place="margin">Act. 5. 9.</note> therefore let no limme of Sathan thinke thus with himselfe, so many yeeres haue I liued an adulterer, a drunkard, a vsurer, a contemner of Gods word, &amp;c. Many a time haue I receiued the Sacrament of Christ his precious body &amp; bloud with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out preparation, without due examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of my selfe, or makeing any diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the Lords body; yet I liue, and I see God prospereth mee, as well as many others, that make the matter a great deale more goodly then my selfe, &amp;c. But I say to thee (and not I, but the Lord) <hi>Be not deceiued, God is not mocked: whatsoeuer a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6. 7.</note>
               <hi>mansoweth, that shall he also reape.</hi> God is not alwayes a word and a blow, but for the most part, he suffereth the wicked to treasure vp sinne, as vsurers vse to coffer
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:20306:19"/> vp their Gold and Siluer, till their bagge of their Iniquity be sealed vp, till their sinnes cry for vengeance in the eares of <note place="margin">Iob. 24. 17.</note> God, as the sinnes of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Babilon.</hi> God long forbare the world in <hi>Noah</hi> his <note place="margin">Gen. 18. 20.</note> time; but at last, hee paied them home with a witnesse. Hee suffered the <hi>Iewes</hi> many yeares in their sinnes; but at last, <note place="margin">Apo. 18. 5.</note> he made an hand with them.</p>
            <p>Let no man then (I say againe) secure himselfe in sinne, because God deferreth his punishments. <hi>Quod differtur non au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertur.</hi> When all is done, a day will come that will pay for all, &amp; as it is in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prouerbe, <hi>The pitcher goeth so long to the water, that it commeth broken home at last.</hi> Though <hi>Adam</hi> for a time hid him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 9.</note> among the Trees of the Garden, yet at length God brought him to light. And though he suffered <hi>Sodom</hi> for a sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, to runne on in their beastlinesse of sin, at last his heauy wrath fell on them. <note place="margin">Gen. 19. 24.</note> And howsoeuer God suffer bad men to goe on in their wickednesse, and to spend their dayes in pleasure and vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; in the end, a day of reckoning will come: and the longer God forbeareth, the greater shall the blow of his venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:20306:19"/> be, when it fals. God hath suffered vs long in our sinnes; and in his mercie, giuen vs many forewarninges of his wrath; as by dearth, vnseasonable Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Plagues and Pestilences, &amp;c. Let vs no longer abuse his patience, but cast downe our selues, in true humiliation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, &amp; turne euery one of vs from that wickednesse that wee haue in our hands, before the decree passe out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vs.</p>
            <p>And let vs acknowledge Gods great mercy in forewarning and forbearing of sinners: though man for whō God hath done so much, be the most sinful crature, yet God is mercifull, he warneth vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he punish vs; he vseth many meanes of mercy, to win vs to himselfe before he take vengeance. He dealeth with vs as a kind father doth with his childrē, he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recteth vs in loue, to amend vs, not to cō<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found vs, nor vtterly to destroy vs, if we haue grace to take any warnings: And as there is a distance betweene seed time &amp; haruest, so God deferreth his fearefull Iudgements, till our sinnes be ripe, and readie for the sith of destruction: yea, &amp; though sometimes hee shew euident to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:20306:20"/> of his wrath, as now by Plague, and vnseasonable Weather; yet, in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, he powreth not out on vs the whole vials of his vengeance, but in his wrath, <note place="margin">Apo. 16. 1, 2, 3, 4, 8, 10, 12. Psal. 78, 8.</note> remembreth mercy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Lord hath a Controuersie with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With whom hath the Lord this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouersie? <hi>with the Inhabitants of the Land.</hi> The whole Inhabitants of the land were the defendants; yea such defendants, that being accused, had neuer a word to speake for them selues.</p>
            <p>See the corrupt and guilty state of the Church sometimes; Sinne had ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spread the Land like a leprosie, or as a spreading canker. So in <hi>Noah</hi> his time <note place="margin">Gen. 6, 12.</note> their sinnes were generall. <hi>All flesh had corrupted his way vpon the earth.</hi> In <hi>Sodom</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen 18.</note> and <hi>Gomorrah</hi> there was no righteous man to be found, for whose sake the Lord might spare the those Cities. In <hi>Ieremy</hi> his time, there was none to be found in Ierusalem <hi>that executed Iudgment, or sought</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 5. 1.</note>
               <hi>for the truth. Dauid</hi> cried out in his time. <hi>Helpe Lord for there is not one godly man left,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 12. 1.</note>
               <hi>for the faithfull are minished from among the Children of men.</hi> The Prophet <hi>Micha</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:20306:20"/> complaineth, <hi>That there was none righteous, all lay in waite for bloud, euery one hunted his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micha. 7. 2. 3 4. 5.</note>
               <hi>brother with a nette.</hi> 4. <hi>The best of them was but as a brier, and the most righteous of them, sharper then a thorne hedge.</hi> 5. <hi>No man could trust his friend nor a counseller, nor her that lay in his bosome.</hi> 6. <hi>The sonne reuiled the father, the daughter rose vp against her mother, the daughter in law against her mother in law, and a mans enemies were the men of his owne house.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs looke among our selues, and suruey our estate, and see if the iniquitie of our times doe not deserue the Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God: and therefore the Lord may as iustly proceed against vs, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <hi>Israel.</hi> Haue not al fortes of people among vs peruerted their wayes? Nay, looke into those places where Gods word is most plentifully preached, and you shal find many Adulterers, Whores, Blasphemers, Drunkards, Contemners of the Word, &amp;c. It is an hard thing to finde a sound <hi>Israelits,</hi> in whom there is <note place="margin">Ioh. 1. 47.</note> no guile. Let vs therefore bewayle the wickednesse of this age, and seeing wee liue among the multitude of the wicked, wee must take heed wee be not infected by them, but labour to do good
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:20306:21"/> among them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With the Inhabitants of the Land.</hi> The controuersie or quarrell that the Lord hath, is with his one Church, &amp; chosen.</p>
            <p>There is no people, nor person so deere to God, but he will punish them, if they sinne against him. <hi>The Lord wil be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at his sanctuary to execute Iudgment. Loe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 9. 6. Ier. 25. 29.</note>
               <hi>I beginne to plague the Cittie, where my name is called vpon. Iudgment must beginne at the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 4. 17.</note>
               <hi>house of God.</hi> Let vs not flatter our selues then and say, we are Gods inheritance, we are Gods people, he will not deale so hardly with vs. But the more thou art in the fauour of God, the greater shalbe thy punishment, if thou sinne against him. Though thou were as neere and deere to God, as the signet on his finger, or the apple of his eye: Yet if there be no remedy, if thou wilt not bee reclaimed from thy sinnes, hee will try an action with thee, he will either pull thee off, or put thee out. Though <hi>Ierusalem</hi> be Gods <note place="margin">Ier. 22. 24.</note> owne Cittie, and <hi>Syon</hi> his beloued, and pleasing spouse, yet if she play the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lot, and will not be reclamed, hee will make her a spectalce of his vengeance. If God then spared not his owne people
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:20306:21"/> the <hi>Iewes,</hi> when they despised his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and set his corrections at naught, what may wee looke for, after so many warnings, and so long abuse of his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, but that hee will execute further Iudgments vpon vs, vnlesse we repent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Because there is no Truth, nor mercy, nor knowledge of God in the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third thing to be considered of, it the cause of the controuersie, which is, the sins of the people, &amp; (as is aboue said) they are here noted to be of two sorts.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Sinnes of Omission.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Sinnes of Commission.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The quarrell was not onely for sinnes committed, but also for duties omitted. God will not onely take vengeance for doing that hee forbiddeth, but also for leauing vndone that he commaundeth to be done. As there are two parts of Gods mercy towards vs, namely boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in bestowing good things on vs; and fauour in with-holding euill from vs: so our seruice towards God standeth its two things; that is, in leauing euill, and cleauing to good. If wee would haue God to doe good to vs, wee must also doe good to others: and if we would not
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:20306:22"/> haue him to lay euill vpon vs, we must not doe euill our selues, nay, wee must not onely cease to doe euill, but also learne to doe well; for these two, the good action (I meane) of leauing euill, and the godly motion of doeing good, issuing from a true fayth, not to merit, but to performe duetie, are as two wings to a sinner, wherewith hee may slie vp to heauen, for as a Bird cannot flie with one wing, nor a man goe with one legge, no more can a sinner come to heauen by the one action of leauing euill, vnlesse he be furthered also by that other of doing good. The barren Fig-tree did not beare <note place="margin">Mat. 21. 19.</note> bad fruit, and yet it was accursed. <hi>Euery tree</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>that bringeth not foorth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 3. 9.</note>
               <hi>good fruit, shalbe hewen downe and cast into the fire.</hi> As good no fruit, as bad furit; for bad fruit, is no fruit of fayth: And therefore it is not said that the Priest &amp; the Leuite did any hurt to the wounded man, but <note place="margin">Luk. 10. 32. 33.</note> that they did him no good; which was a kind of hurting him. In the generall Iudgement sentence of condemnation shall not passe vpon the reprobate be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they tooke ought away from the poore, but because they omitted duties of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:20306:22"/> charity, which they should haue per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed vnto them, which equalled taking away from them. Christ the Iudge shal not then say to thē on his left hand, <hi>Depart yee cursed into euerlasting fire &amp;c. For I was hungry, because you tooke from mee that I should eat;</hi> but when I was hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, you gaue me no meate: which in a sort, is taking away of meate: Neither shall hee say, I was naked because you <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 22▪ 23.</note> robbed me of my garments; but I was naked, and you clothed me not: shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that to be able, and not willing to cloth the poore, may bee termed a rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of them.</p>
            <p>The rich Glutton was not condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned because hee tooke any thing away from poore <hi>Lazarus,</hi> but because he gaue him nothing in his need. And the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet heere, telles the people of <hi>Israel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 21.</note> that the Lord hath a Controuersie with them, not onely because they brake out by Swearing, Lying, Killing, Stealing, Whoring, and doing that which God forbade to be done; but also because they fayled in those duties which God required: <hi>There was no truth, mercy, nor</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:20306:23"/>
               <hi>knowledge of God in the Land.</hi> The reason is, because God did not onely create vs to glorifie him by abstaining from euill, but by doing good also. Christ died, and rose againe for vs, not onely that wee should die to sinne; but also that wee should liue againe vnto righteousnesse: for what is it the better, if we die to sin, if we stay there, and rise not againe to righteousnesse of life?</p>
            <p>The vse hereof should teach vs to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour not onely to cleanse our selues <hi>from all filthynesse of the flesh and spirit, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so to grow vp vnto full holinesse in the feare</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 7. 1.</note>
               <hi>of God That wee should not onely cease to doe euill, hut also learne to doe well. Not only put</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay. 1. 16. 17.</note>
               <hi>off the old man with his workes, but also put on the new man, which after God is created in righteousnesse and true holynesse.</hi> Ephe. 4. 22. 23. 24. Col. 3. 9. 10.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this serueth to reproue the proud <hi>Pharises</hi> of our time, which boast themselues of their vpright dealing and lyuing, as thus: I thanke God, I am no prophaner of the Saboth, no adulterer, no whore, I am no theefe, murtherer, drunkard; I neuer did harme to any &amp; e. Therefore, they thinke, God is behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:20306:23"/> to them; But thou must not onely abstaine from euill, but also do good: &amp; as the Eagle casteth her bill, and renueth her youth, &amp; the Snake strippeth off her Skin, and becommeth-smooth; so must thou cast off the old rags of <hi>Adams</hi> cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, and put on the roabes of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teousnesse, euen that wedding garment, the Innocency of Christ, without which none shalbe admitted to the mariage feast. Examine thy selfe then, not onely what sinnes thou hast not done, but also what good thou hast done; It is not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough that thou hast not prophaned the Saboth day, but also that thou hast sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified it. Brag not thy selfe that hast not oppressed the poore, not taken any thing from them, but tell me also what good thou hast done to them? If we <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 20.</note> could see the proud and prodigal leaue off their prid and prodigality, and giue of their superfluity to the poore: if we could see whore-masters leaue off their filthy kinde of liuing, and now glorifie God in their soules &amp; bodies, which are <note place="margin">Luk. 19. 8.</note> Gods. If we could find couetous misers and vsurers like to <hi>Zacheus,</hi> liberall in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing &amp; ready in restoring their il gotted
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:20306:24"/> goods remoouing their fences, turning downe their incroched furrowes, which <note place="margin">Iob. 31. 38.</note> cry and complaine against them, and emptying (to good vses) their Houses and Coffers of their cursed Wealth wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly gotten, &amp;c. then wee needed not doubt, but God would let his sute fall, the Controuersie would cease, and wee should be reconciled to the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Because there is no trueth, &amp;c.</hi> Moreouer here obserue; he accuseth them first with the sinnes of the second Table, and then of the first. Where we may see how the Lord dealeth with Hipocrites; he doth not first charge them with sinnes of the first Table, but of the second. Hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites will be very forward in outward shew of the workes of the first Table, and often frequent publike Assemblies, without care of their carriage or conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation, like <hi>Sathan</hi> in shew of an Angell of light. The Lord was euen aweary of the outward sacrifices, seruises, &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> and why? Because their hands were full of Blood. <hi>Esa.</hi> 1. 5. They made a goodly outward shew: <hi>Wherfore haue wee fasted</hi> (say they) <hi>and thou seest it</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay. 58. 3, 4. 5.</note>
               <hi>not?</hi> The Lord reiecteth their outward
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:20306:24"/> seruice, because it was but in hipocrisie.</p>
            <p>There is none that make so faire an outward shew of Gods worship &amp; ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, as Hipocrits doe: They are like gilded Pots, full of poyson; like the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Sodom,</hi> touch them, &amp; they turne to dust; like Strumpets, which in shew seeme honest: <hi>Kains</hi> sacrifice in outward <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 3. 4.</note> appearance was like <hi>Habels.</hi> The harlot will also offer her peace offerings and <note place="margin">Pro. 7. 14.</note> vowes. <hi>Iesabel</hi> will haue her fast. 1. <hi>Kin.</hi> 21. 9 and so will the Pharises. <hi>Ananias</hi> &amp; <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 6. 16. Math. 9. 14.</note> will offer to the Church in shew. <hi>Act</hi> 5. 2. Many will not sticke to be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumcised, with the Sychemits to get <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 34. 24.</note> But you must know that it is not the painting of a filthy sepulcher that make it sweet, nor the proud decking of a strumpet that makes her an honest wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, nor the beauty of a Peacock, that proueth him to be the best Bird. Deceiue not your selues then, the same God that requireth the duties of the first Table, would not haue the duties of the second vndone. As we should be forward in the worship and seruice of God, so also wee must bee carefull to deale vprightly with men. Your comming to Church to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:20306:25"/> holy exercises, is abhomination before God, if it be but in shew to seeme holy: It is not the lifting vp of your eyes, nor holding vp of your hands, will serue the turne, vnlesse hand and heart goe togeather. None so cerimonious as Hipocrites, none will seeme more holy then they: but let vs see that our life and conuersation before men, expresse that which in word &amp; outward shew we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fesse; let profession &amp; practise goe hand in hand; those whom God hath ioyned togeather, let no man put asunder.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Because there is no Truth.</hi> Strange, there was no Truth among them. This is an hard accusation: What, no Truth? No doubt but there was some Truth; but Falsehood was so general, that there see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be no Truth. <hi>Esay</hi> complained in his time, <hi>That no man contended for Truth; and that Truth was fallen in the street.</hi> Esay 59. 4. 14. <hi>Ieremy</hi> likewise in his time; <hi>That Truth was perished and cleane gone.</hi> Ier. 7. 18. Christ himselfe sayth: <hi>When the Sonne of man commeth, shall hee finde Fayth on the earth?</hi> Luk. 18. 8.</p>
            <p>Neuer lesse Truth, nor true dealing among men in any age; vniust dealing
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:20306:25"/> and cosonag not more current among Turkes and Infidels, then now among Christians.</p>
            <p>He is accounted but a foole that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deale cunningly and craftily to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue others. Yea some are grone so im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, that they are not ashamed to say. That hee which will not hold with the Hare, and runne with Hound; hee that cannot carry two Faces vnder one Hood and play the <hi>Ambo-dexter,</hi> is not fit to liue in this world among men: but I say, hee is fitter to dwell with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels in Hell. The sinnes of the <hi>Iewes</hi> were neuer more red-ripe then ours; we liue as if we should neuer die, nor come to appeare before the Iudgement seate of <hi>Iesus Christ</hi> the iust Iudge, to giue an account.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Truth</hi> is a part of the Image of God, and False-hood is a part of the Image of the Diuell: wee are members one of an other; <hi>Let no man deceiue his Brother, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God is the auenger of all such.</hi> 1. <hi>Thes.</hi> 4. 6. If a man could doe it so cunningly, that it could not be seene, yet God will punish it. Seeing then, that Truth is a part of the Image of God, he cannot be
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:20306:26"/> a good Christian that hath not Truth in wordes and deedes. Wee are called to the hope of eternall life by the word of Truth.</p>
            <p>How miserable a thing is it then, when there is no truth among men? Is it not with vs as it was in <hi>Dauids</hi> time? <hi>The faythfull are minished from among the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men</hi> (for the most part,) <hi>They flatter with their tongues, and dissemble in their dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble harts. Psa.</hi> 12. 1. 2. Is it not amongst vs, as it was with the <hi>Iewes</hi> in <hi>Ieremies</hi> time? May not a man runne vp and downe, <note place="margin">Iere. 5. 1.</note> and search the streetes of euery Cittie and Towne, yea through the whole Land, &amp; finde but a few men that seeke the Truth: But, <hi>Vers.</hi> 27. <hi>As a Cage is full of Birdes, so a man shall finde many houses stoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi>
               <note place="margin">vers. 27.</note>
               <hi>with that is gotten by decept,</hi> and craftie trickes, without Truth or conscience, so as we may iustly cry out and complaine with the same <hi>Ieremy: They be all Adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, &amp; an assembly of rebels.</hi> 3. <hi>And they bend</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 9. 2, 3, 4, 5.</note>
               <hi>their tongues like their Bowes for lyes: but they haue no courage for the Truth vpon the earth, for they proceed from euill to worse, and they haue not knowne mee, saith the Lord.</hi> 4. <hi>Let euery one take heed to his neighbour, and trust</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:20306:26"/>
               <hi>thou not in any Brother: for euery Brother will vse decept, and euery friend will deale de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiptfully.</hi> 5. <hi>And euery one will deceiue his friend, and will not speake the Truth, for they haue taught their tongues to speake lies, and take great Paines to doe wickedly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Want of Truth is such, that it is a vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all thing to say, <hi>Wee know not whom wee may trust.</hi> Whereas in times past words were sufficient, a man might trust his neighbour, vpon his word, now bonds will not serue. Truth is a faire Flower, (but now a dayes) it groweth in the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of few mens hearts; and therefore seldome seene sprouting out, either in their words or deeds. What is become of that ancient Truth and faithfulnesse of subiects towards their Prince? If it were as it ought to bee, we should not bee acquainted with so many damnable and dangerous treasons and conspira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies against Christian Princes.</p>
            <p>If there were that Truth betweene husband and wife, as should bee, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill would not dance at so many wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings as he doth, where hands are ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and not hearts: Neither should we heare of so many poysonings, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:20306:27"/> adulteries, and disagrements be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man &amp; wife, as are daylie put in practise. Is not that <hi>quandam Truth</hi> of seruants towardst their Maisters, quite banished, and worne out, so that wee can neither finde trustinesse in their laboures, nor truth in their dealings. Truth is <hi>Rara auis in terris, nigroque simillima cygno,</hi> and therefore one sayd well, <hi>Multis annis iam peractis nulla fides est in factis, mel in ore, verba lactis, fel in corde, fraus in factis:</hi> Many yeeres past and gone, faith in deeds there is none, hony in mouth, words sweet, gall in heart, deceipt in deed. If therefore the Lord had a controuersie with the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of the Land of Israell, because there was no Truth among them: much more may he haue with vs whose state is so bad, and yet haue had the light of the Gospell so long amongst vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nor Mercie.</hi> The next thing whereof they are indicted, is want of Mercy, a fruit also of the second Table. <hi>Mercy</hi> among men, is an inward affection of the heart, taking part with thy brother, and hauing a fellow-feeling of his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sery, as if it were thine owne: Such was
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:20306:27"/> the mercy of Christ towards the people, for that he had suffered hunger himselfe: <hi>I haue compassion</hi> (saith hee) <hi>on the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, because they haue now continued with me three dayes, &amp; haue nothing to eate. Mar.</hi> 8. 2 This mercy in man, towards man, is an excellent thing, there is no sacrifice nor seruice acceptable to GOD without it; wee need not to goe by-wayes, nor of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer sacrifices in vaine. <hi>He hath shewed thee (O man) what is good, and what the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth of thee; surely, to doe Iustly, and to loue Merey, and to humble thy selfe to walke with God: Micha.</hi> 6. 8. It is required of a Christian, not onely to bee mercifull, but also to loue mercy. <hi>Now therefore as the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eph. 4. 31.</note>
               <hi>elect of God</hi> (saith the Apostle) <hi>holy and beloued, put on bowels of mercy, Col.</hi> 3. 12. Mercy should bee in the bowels, it should proceed from a feeling of the miseries of others. There were some that shut vp their bowels of mercy. So that <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3. 17.</note> neither any thing could enter in, to mooue them to mercy, nor goe forth, to doe good to others. There are some whose bowels are cruelty, <hi>Pro.</hi> 12. 10. and some againe, that haue no bowels of Mercy. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. 1. But they that are
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:20306:28"/> Gods Children follow the counsell of the Apostle: put on the bowels of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. In Mercie, there are two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>To see the miserie of others.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>To take compassion.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>A child of God will see with his eyes, and pitty with his heart. <hi>Diues</hi> saw the Misery of <hi>Lazarus, Luk</hi> 16. 20. but shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no Mercy. The <hi>Priest</hi> and the <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite</hi> saw the Miserie of the wounded man, and passed by, and shewed no Mercie: but that good <hi>Samaritane</hi> did <note place="margin">Luk. 10. 31, 32, 33, 34.</note> not onely see him lie wounded, but hee also went to him, hee poured Wine and Oyle into his Woundes, set him on his owne Beast, brought him to a common Inne, and made prouision for him, (at his owne charges:) heere was true Mercy.</p>
            <p>There be many things may moue vs to Mercifulnesse: first, because in shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy, we imitate God: <hi>Bee merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi> (saith Christ) <hi>as your Father in heauen is mercifull.</hi> Luk. 6. 36. <hi>And so shall you be the childred of your Father that is in heauen. Math.</hi> 5. 45. If we call God our Father, and professe our selues to be his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, then let vs be mercifull as hee is;
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:20306:28"/> wee can no way so neerely represent God, as in being mercifull: a mercifull man is the best image of God, and a child of God in deed. Wee say, that Child is most like his Father, which doth neerest represent him in Face and countenance: Now, mercy in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, is called the Face or Countenance of God: <hi>God be mercifull vnto vs, and blesse vs, and shew vs the light of his Countenance, and be Mercifull vnto vs. Psal.</hi> 67. 1. So they that are most inclined to Mercy, are most like to God, and no doubt, but they are Gods children. Such a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full man, such a child of God was <hi>Tobias, who sent out his sonne to fetch in the poore, which remembred God, to eate with him, and tarried for their comming. Tobi.</hi> 2. 2. Such a mercifull man was <hi>Iob, Hee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the poore that cried, and the father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse, and him that had none to helpe him, Iob.</hi> 29. 12. 13. 15. <hi>The blessing of him that was ready to perish came vpon him, and he caused the Widdowes heart to reioyce. Verse</hi> 13. <hi>Hee was the eyes to the blind, and feet to the lame, Verse,</hi> 15. <hi>He was a father to the poore, Vers.</hi> 16. <hi>He restrained not the poore of their desire, neither caused hee the eyes of the Widdow to</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:20306:29"/>
               <hi>faile. Iob.</hi> 31. 16. 18, 19. 20 32 <hi>He did not eate his morsels alone, but the fatherlesse also did eate thereof; he would not see any perish for want of cloathing, or any poore without co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uering, the loynes of the naked blessed him, because hee was couered with the fleece of his sheepe. Hee suffered not the stranger to lodge in the street, but opened his doores to him that went by the way. Verse</hi> 32. But now pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Iob,</hi> and mercifull <hi>Tobias</hi> are dead and gone, who imitated God, and bare the Image of God, in beeing mercifull, and no doubt were Gods Children, and many an vnmercifull <hi>Nabal</hi> is start vp in their steed, who thinke all too little to themselues, and euery little too much for the poore.</p>
            <p n="2">2 A second thing that should moue vs hereunto is, because that when wee execute the workes of mercie we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Gods instruments, and it is an <note place="margin">Mat. 24. 45.</note> excellent thing to be the Instrument of God, to doe good to others. God hath <note place="margin">Luk 12. 42.</note> put the rich men of this world, in trust with the wealth of this world, not to the end that they should either be in loue with it, or abuse it to prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gality, but that they should, as Gods
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:20306:29"/> Instruments, distribute to the necessity of the Saints.</p>
            <p n="3">3 A third motiue to mercifulnesse is, because what wee doe to the poore, Christ doth acknowledge it to bee done to himselfe. If thou giue but a morsell of Bread, or a Cuppe of water: If thou giue but the meanest almes, <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 40.</note> Christ doth acknowledge it done to himselfe. If wee would consider that in feeding the poore, wee seed Christ; in cloathing them, we cloath Christ; in lodging them, wee lodge Christ, &amp;c. how cheerefully then would men doe it?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, the consideration of Gods mercy towards vs, should mooue vs to bee mercifull to others. God <note place="margin">1. Reg. 8. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> sheweth mercie on vs that are his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to the end wee should bee merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to his friends: Christ reprooued <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 33.</note> the vnmercifull seruant, <hi>Oughtest not thou also to haue had compassion on thy fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, euen as I had pitty on thee?</hi> If wee would consider that God is often mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to vs, when in Iustice he might take vengeance on vs, or vtterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy vs, it would cut off all cruelty,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:20306:30"/> and mooue vs to bee mercifull to our bretheren, and thinke this, God hath beene mercifull to me in may things, why should not I also bee mecifull to my poore neighbour?</p>
            <p n="5">5 Fiftly, because the practise of mercy is a token of true Religion, <hi>Pure Religion and vndefiled before God euen the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 1. 27.</note>
               <hi>Father is this, to visite the Fatherlesse, and Widowes in their aduersity, and to keepe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe vnspotted of the world.</hi> If thou wilt try thine hart whether thou be truly religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, see how thou art affected with the lustes of concupiscence, and whether thou haue a care to cherish the poore, Widowes, and fatherlesse, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue the needy members of Christ; who so hath these practises, is truely religious.</p>
            <p n="6">6 The sixth and last motiue which may moue vs to mercifulnesse, is, the promises made to the mercifull, which are often set downe in the Scriptures, by way of comparison. Sometimes Mercy is compared to a seed time, or sowing, <hi>He that soweth sparingly, shal reape sparingly: and hee that soweth liberally, shall reape also liberally.</hi> Also he <hi>that findeth</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 9. 10.</note>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:20306:30"/>
               <hi>seed to the sower will minister likewise bread for food, and multiply your seed, and increase the fruites of year beneuolence.</hi> 10. Remember when thou giuest to the poore, then thou sowest spirituall seed; &amp; that he which giueth seed to the sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er &amp; causeth it to increase, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, might lie, and rotte vnder the clods, hee will also increase what thou hast, with a blessing: And as that seed which is cast into the groud, may seeme to bee cast away, were not Gods bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing vpon it, so though what thou gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uest to the poore, may seeme to bee lost, yet God will restore it againe with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage. It is also compared to a sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. <hi>To doe good, and to distribute, forget not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 13. 16.</note>
               <hi>for with such sacrifice God is well pleased.</hi> As God smelled the sweet sauour of <hi>Noah</hi> his sacrifice. So if thou offer <note place="margin">Gen. 8. 21.</note> this sacrifice of Mercy, it will yeeld a sweete odour vnto God, and God will accept it. It is wonderfull how vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull and hard hearted men are this way, and how lauish and liberall where they should not; when <hi>Aaron</hi> had yeelded to make a golden Celfe, the people were ready not onely to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:20306:31"/> giue their superfluous things, but also their necessarie lewels, as their Eare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes: So ready and liberall were they <note place="margin">Exod. 32. 3.</note> also in times past, to set vp Idols, and guilded Images, at their great charges, and to goe many miles to offer vnto them: Shall not their liberalitie in things not commanded, but vtterly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden, condemne our foolishnesse, which spend so much in pride &amp; super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous pampering of our paunches? We care not what we giue &amp; lash out to those Idols the Backe &amp; the Belly; but our hearts are grieued to giue a little to <hi>Iesus Christ,</hi> in his members. If men would cut them selues shorter this way, and content themselues with necessary Food and Rayment, then should they <note place="margin">1. Tim. 6. 8.</note> see Gods blessings vpon this spirituall sowing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He that hath Mercy vpon the poore</hi> (saith <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 17.</note>
               <hi>Salomon) lendeth vnto the Lord, and the Lord will recompence him that which he hath giuen.</hi> This is a godly kind of Vsurie, and would God this Vsurie, might eate vp our other Vsurie, as in <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his Dreame, the leane Kine did the fatte. <note place="margin">Gen. 41 4.</note> As hee that lendes vpon Vsurie loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:20306:31"/> for gaine: so hee that is Mercifull to the poore, may expect a Spirituall gaine, and a plentifull Haruest.</p>
            <p>Mer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cy is also compared to Wate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. <hi>The liberall person shall haue plentie, and he that Watereth shall also haue raine.</hi> If <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 25.</note> we drop but one drop of Mercy vpon our poore brethren, God will open the Windowes of heauen vpon vs, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and refresh vs with many blessings. It is promised to the Mercifull, <hi>That their light shall breake foorth as the morning,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esa. 58. 8 9, 10, 11. 12.</note>
               <hi>and their health shall grow speedily; their righteousnesse shall goe before them, and the glory of the Lord shall imbrace them.</hi> 9. <hi>Then they shall call, and the Lord shall answere, they shall cry, and hee shall say, heere I am.</hi> 10. <hi>Their light shall spring out in the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and their darkenesse shall be as the noone day.</hi> 11. <hi>The Lord will guide them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, and satisfie their soule in drought, and make fatte their bones, they shall be like a watered garden, and like a spring of Water, whose waters fayle not. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They shall haue graces outward and inward. <hi>Hee that withdraweth the Corne</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 11. 26.</note> (saith <hi>Salomon the people will curse him, but blessing shalbe vpon the head of him, that</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:20306:32"/>
               <hi>giueth food.</hi> And <hi>Hee that giueth to the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 27.</note>
               <hi>poore, shall not lacke. If thou shew Mercie to the poore, maymed, lame, and blind, thou shalt be blessed, and God will reward thee.</hi> And our Sauiour pronounceth <hi>the Mercifull,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 14 14. Math. 5. 7.</note>
               <hi>blessed: for they shall obtaine Mercie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These Promises of God made to the Mercifull thus then considered, I say to thee in a word, as the Prophet <hi>Malachit</hi> speaketh in an other matter: Bee thou Mercifull to thy poore Neighbour, sow that spirituall Seed, offer that sweete Sacrifice; Water and refresh the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry soule: yea, <hi>Cast thy Bread vpon the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclesi. 11. 1.</note>
               <hi>face of the Waters.</hi> And then proue the Lord therewith, <hi>if he will not open the Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mall. 3. 10.</note>
               <hi>of Heauen vnto thee, and poure thee out a blessing without measure,</hi> and approoue himselfe a true God in his promises.</p>
            <p>And seeing Mercie is such an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent thing, it serueth to condemne the crueltie, and vnmercifulnesse of many in our time, which carry rauening af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections; and therefore are compared <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 15.</note> to cruell Beastes, as to hungry Lyons, Beares, and Wolues, because they haue <note place="margin">Zeph. 3. 3.</note> no more Mercy then rauening Lyons, Beares, and Wolues, in the euening, so
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:20306:32"/> greedy, that they leaue not the bones till the morning. It is lamentable to see how the Rich oppresse the Poore, and approoue themselues to haue no more Mercie then Beastes: But let all such vnmercifull wretches consider with feare and trembling, in what miserable state they stand.</p>
            <p>First, their Prayers are abhominable: <hi>Though thou make many Prayers</hi> (saith the <note place="margin">Esay. 1. 15.</note> Lord) <hi>I will not heare you, because your hands</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 7. 13.</note>
               <hi>are full of blood.</hi> God reiecteth, and will not heare the Prayers of the Vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full: <note place="margin">Esa. 59. 2. 3.</note> so long as they haue bloody fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, their Prayers are abhominable; <hi>They haue not the spirit of Prayer, which eate</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 14. 4.</note>
               <hi>vp the people of God▪ as a man would eate Bread.</hi> How horrible and fearefull a Iudgement is it, to haue the doores of Gods Graces shut vp against vs, and the the Walles of his Fauour and Mercie locked vp from vs, that wee cannot draw the Water of life: Wee haue none other Messenger to God▪ but our Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers: but Vnmercifulnesse, maketh our Prayers to returne voyde; which is an heauie Iudgement. If then there be any among you, that carry an Vnmercifull
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:20306:33"/> affection, first let the oppressed▪ goe free. <hi>Wash your bloody and vnmercifull</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay 58. 6. Esay. 1. 16.</note>
               <hi>hands,</hi> else, neuer offer your Prayers vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. How dare you come to Christ by Prayer, while you deale Vnmerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully with him in his poore members? For as they that feed the Poore, feed Christ; so they that deale Vnmerciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with the poore, doe wrong to Christ: and hee, <hi>That stoppeth his eares at the crie of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 21. 13.</note>
               <hi>the Poore, shall also crie himselfe, and not be heard.</hi> As then thou wouldest haue God to accept of, and to heare thy Prayers, when thou criest to him in thy greatest need: so see that thou also open thine eares, thine heart and hand too, at the cry and complaint of thy di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stressed poore Neighbour.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Vnmercifulnesse maketh a wise man madde. If a man haue neuer so many good guiftes, if he haue once an <note place="margin">Eccle. 7. 9.</note> Vnmercifull and rauening minde, all his Wisedome, Learning, and other good guiftes are buried and lost. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore euery Vnmercifull man is an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theist, <hi>They are resolued there is no God:</hi> For, if they thought there were either <note place="margin">Psal. 14. 1.</note> God, or Diuell, Heauen, or Hell, they
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:20306:33"/> would not deale so Vnmercifully with others as they doe. These are they whom <hi>Salomon</hi> speaketh of: <hi>There is a generation, whose teeth are swordes.</hi> Hee <note place="margin">Pro 30. 14.</note> compareth them to beastes, as if they had teeth like swords or kniues.</p>
            <p>It is true then, that vnmercifull men banish God out of their hearts, and therfore they are carried with the spirit of madnesse, and cruelty, God is not in all their thoughts, neither are they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded that vnmercifulnesse is a sinne.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the vnmercifull man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoketh God to take vengeance on him by temporall punishments, and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in this life: <hi>The bloudy and deceipt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 55. 23.</note>
               <hi>man, shall not liue out halfe his dayes: God will auenge them that are vnmercifully delt withall; and that quickly. Thou shalt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 18. 8.</note>
               <hi>not</hi> (saith the Lord) <hi>doe iniurie to a stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, neither oppresse him, for yee were stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in the Land of Egipt. Yee shall not trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 22. 21, 22. 23, 24.</note>
               <hi>any Widow, nor fatherlesse Child, if thou vex or trouble such, and so hee call and cry vnto me, I will surely heare his cry. Then shall my wrath bee kindled, and I will kill you with the sword, and your wiues shalbe Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, and your Children fatherlesse.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="60" facs="tcp:20306:34"/>
            <p>It is too common a thing to see stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, fatherlesse Children, &amp; Widowes vnmercifully delt withall. Strangers (for the most part) are strangely looked on; and as for Orphans, let a man die, and commit his children (with suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent portions) to the protection of his brother or neerest kinsman, for the most part, they will vnckle, and Couzin the poore Orphans of that their father left them, and often vse them worse then seruants. Is it not a Iust thing with God, to arrainge such before his Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment seate, and plead and proue against them, that they haue no Mercy; and therefore shall finde as little Mercy at Gods hands? And is the state of Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes any better, for the most part; are they not also subiect to wronges, and vnmercifull dealing? But let them com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort themselues, God hath promised to bee <hi>a Father to the Fatherlesse,</hi> defendeth the cause of the Widowes, and looketh <note place="margin">Psal. 68. 5. Psa. 146. 9. Mal. 3. 5. Ecclesi. 35. 15. Deut. 27. 19</note> vpon the wrongs done to them, and will reuenge them. <hi>Doth not</hi> (saith <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rach) the teares runne downe the Widowes Cheekes, and her cry is against him that cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed them: for from her Cheeks doe they goe vp</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:20306:34"/>
               <hi>into heauen, &amp; the Lord which heareth them, doth accept them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Israelits</hi> being vnmercifully delt withall by the <hi>Egiptians,</hi> cryed in their <note place="margin">Exod. 2, 23. 24. Exod. 15. 25</note> misery, and God heard them, tooke the matter into his owne hand, and reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them. <hi>Dauid</hi> delt vnmercifully with his subiect and seruant <hi>Vrias;</hi> but God would not suffer him to escape vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punished: Though <hi>Dauid</hi> was a King, <hi>Ʋrias</hi> a subiect; <hi>Dauid</hi> aliue, <hi>Vrias</hi> dead; yet God auenged the wrong done to <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12.</note> him, euen vpon the King himselfe. Then God will not suffer the Vnmercifull <note place="margin">1. Thes. 4. 6</note> man to escape, <hi>The Lord is the auenger of all such. The poore committeth himselfe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 10. 14.</note>
               <hi>thee</hi> (saith <hi>Dauid,) for thou art the hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the friendlesse.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though the poore neither curse, nor cry vengeance against them that deale Vnmercifully with them; yet God will stand for them. <hi>Now for the oppression of the needie, and because of the sighes of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 12 5.</note>
               <hi>poore, I will vp</hi> (sayth the Lord,) <hi>and will set at libertie him whom the wicked hath sna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;</hi> yea rather then Gods Iustice in this poynt should sayle, <hi>The Stones and timber in the house of vnmerciful men, shal cry</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:20306:35"/>
               <hi>for vengeance against them, and bring a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hab. 2. 11. 12.</note>
               <hi>Iudgement vpon them.</hi> There is a woe pronounced against such, God hath a <note place="margin">Micha. 2. 1. 2. 3.</note> Plague, and a vengeance for them, which shall sticke close to them; the Lands and Goods which they haue gotten by vnmercifull dealing, shall be accursed vnto them in the end: <hi>Yea, the Furrowes of their Land, shalbe accursed vnto</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 31. 38.</note>
               <hi>them. Ahab</hi> and <hi>Iezabell</hi> dealt vnmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully <note place="margin">2 King 21. 9. 10. 13.</note> with <hi>Naboth, cozoned him of his Land, &amp; his life too:</hi> But Gods vengeance slept not long, they had small ioy of their bloody purchase; the wrath of <note place="margin">Iohn. 33. 36.</note> God aboad on them. And as when a mercifull man doth cloath the naked, <note place="margin">Iob. 31. 20.</note> though he be vnthankefull, yet his loynes that were naked, and now cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed, will blesse him that cloathed them. So when vnmercifull men take that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the Poore, which should cloath their Backes, or fill their Bellies, though they take it patiently; yet their hungry Bellies, and naked Backes, will plead Vengeance, &amp; God will reuenge the wrong done to them. If then thou wouldest not haue Gods heauie Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to fall vpon thee: bee not an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:20306:35"/> dealer, because the Lord is the auenger of all such.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, as vnmercifull men shall not escape the Iudgements of God in this life; so at last, death commeth: and when an vnmercifull man dieth, his state shalbe like to <hi>Iehoiakim,</hi> the sonne of <hi>Iosia,</hi> King of <hi>Judah,</hi> the people will <note place="margin">Iere. 22. 18. 19.</note> not mourne for him, <hi>Alas brother,</hi> Or (ah) <hi>what a losse hath the Country of him, but hee shall haue the buriall of an Asse.</hi> As their dead Asses were cast out of <hi>Ierusa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> least they should infect the ayre, with their smell; so vnmercifull vsurers were in times past, denied the honor of Christian buriall.</p>
            <p>Lastly, these are but small matters, but vnlesse vnmercifull men repent, they shalbe shut out of Gods King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; <hi>Thus saith the Lord, yee eate with the Bloud, and lift vp your eyes towardes your</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 33. 25 1. Cor. 6. 10.</note>
               <hi>Idoles, and shead Bloud: shall yee then possesse the Land?</hi> And the Apostle <hi>Iames</hi> saith, <hi>There shalbe Judgement mercilesse, to him</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam 2. 13.</note>
               <hi>that sheweth no mercy.</hi> If at the Iudgement day they shalbe shut out of heauen, which haue not giuen to the needy, what Iudgements remaine for those that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:20306:36"/> haue dealt vnmercifully with them? <note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> shall they enter in? no, they shall be sure to be shut out. And God will not leaue them so: What, not in Hell? Yes, for Hell shalbe their possession: but thats not all, for God will curse them also in their posterity. The curse of God <note place="margin">Iob. 27. 13. 14.</note> wil so consume them, &amp; their posterity, that nothing shall remaine but the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of Gods vengeance. These are no inuented shar-babs, the Lord hath sworne by the excellency of <hi>Iacob, That</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos. 8. 7. 8</note>
               <hi>he will neuer forget, but punish all oppressors and vnmercifull dealers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Seeing then that vnmercifulnesse brings such heauy Iudgements of God with it, if euer wee looke to escape his rod and punishments, and to be recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled vnto him, let vs after the counsel of the Prophet, <hi>Wash,</hi> and make our selues <note place="margin">Esay. 1. 16. 17</note> cleane from that bloudy sinne of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifulnesse, and then the Lord will speake comfortably to our consciences, and tell vs, <hi>Though our sins were as Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sin, they shalbe made white as Snow, &amp; though</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay 1 18.</note>
               <hi>they were red like Scarlet, they shalbe as Well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And heere wee may also iurney our estate, and let our owne consciences
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:20306:36"/> answere for vs, whether the Lord may not as iustly charge some of vs with this sinne of vnmercifulnesse, as euer he did the people of <hi>Israel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What Mercy with some vnmercifull Land-lords, who turne housing into grasing, &amp; make more account of their beasts then of their bretheren. So that, as the Poet <hi>Ouid</hi> writ concerning <hi>Troy,</hi> after the destruction of it, <hi>Estque seges vbi</hi> Troia <hi>fuit,</hi> Now growes Corne where <hi>Troy</hi> stood: So in many places, passengers, may point with their fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and say, In this pasture of groud stood such a towne, and there another; and now Cattle feed, where sometimes christians dwelt. Such vnmerciful land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lords deale with their Tenaunts as Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teners doe with their vessels, who draw them till they bee empty, and then tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble them out a doores. Is this brotherly compassion? Is this to haue a fellow-feeling of the miseries of others? Is this to doe to others, as wee would they should doe vnto vs?</p>
            <p>What Mercy with vnmercifull Vsu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, but cruelty vnder a colour of Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse? They are the Diuels Alcumists,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:20306:37"/> they can change other mens goods into their owne. The Lord expresly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth Vsurie in his Law, and shall wee make no conscience to vse it? <hi>If thou lend Money to my people,</hi> (saith the Lord) <note place="margin">Exo. 22. 25.</note>
               <hi>that is, to the poore with thee, thou shalt not be an Ʋsurer vnto him; thou shalt not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presse him with Ʋsurie.</hi> And againe. <hi>If thy brother be impouerished, or fallen into de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay, &amp;c. thou shalt take no Ʋsury of him, nor</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leui. 25. 35. 36.</note>
               <hi>vantage; but thou shalt feare thy God, that thy brother may liue with thee.</hi> And in Deutronomie: <hi>Thou shalt not giue to Vsury,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deu 23. 19.</note>
               <hi>to thy brother; as vsury of Money, vsury of Meate vsury of any thing that is put to vsury.</hi> If God forbad Vsury among the <hi>Jewes,</hi> because they were brethren; much more among vs Christians, because wee are brethren in Christ. And if the breach of Gods Commaundements bring with it destruction both of body and soule; then Vsurie, which God expresly for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids in his Law, deserueth destruction both of body and soule. <hi>Dauid</hi> asketh the question, <hi>Lord, who shall dwell in thy Tabernacle, and who shall rest vpon thy holy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 15. 1. 5.</note>
               <hi>Mountaine?</hi> and maketh answere, verse 5. <hi>He that giueth not his money to Vsury. &amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:20306:37"/> If hee that giueth not his Money to Vsurie, shall dwell in the Lords Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle, and rest in his holy Mountaine; then it must needes follow, that hee which giueth his Money to Vsury, shall be shut out of Gods Tabernacle, and not rest in his holy Mountaine. And if hee <hi>That hath not giuen foorth vpon Vsurie, neither hath taken any increase, shall liue</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 18. 8, 9, 13.</note>
               <hi>with the Lord for euer; then hee that hath giuen foorth vpon Vsurie, and taken increase, shall not liue.</hi> vers. 13, <hi>but die, his blood shall</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 15. 8. Math. 5. 42. Luk. 6. 35. Psal. 37. 26.</note>
               <hi>be vpon him.</hi> Our Sauiour Christ com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds vs to lend, looking for nothing againe. <hi>A good man</hi> (saith <hi>Dauid) is euer Mercifull, and lendeth.</hi> Mercy and Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding should goe togeather: wee must lend to others to better their estate, not to better our selues, and begger our brethren. As the law of Diuorce was permitted in <hi>Moses</hi> his time, because of the hardnesse of their heartes; so is Vsurie suffered, but not alowed by the Lawes of our Land, because of the hardnesse of mens heartes, to set a bond, or meere to mens couetousnesse, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause there is no Mercie among them. And as there is no Mercy with this vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifull
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:20306:38"/> brood, in forcing men to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay more then the principall which they borrowed; so if the borrower vpon extremitie breake day with them, he had as good be halfe hanged, then will they play vpon him with their crueltie; then shall he be sure to be sued vpon forfeytures, no remedie but either pay, or to Prison; they will either haue his Coyne, or his Carkaise.</p>
            <p>How dare such vnmercifull wretches looke vp towards Heauen, hope to be saued by the death of Christ, or cry to God for mercy in their miserie, while they suffer their owne flesh and blood, their brethren and sisters in the Lord, to lie in Prison, for not payment of a litle plefe; which at the day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <note place="margin">Iames. 5. 3.</note> shall witnesse against them, and condemne them for euer: yea, the very Stones of the Prison, shall cry venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance against them, for their crueltie: It is lawfull indeed for euery man to <note place="margin">Haba. 2 11.</note> demaund his owne; but to doe it in Mercie, not with extremitie, as that Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant who tooke his fellow Seruant by the throat, saying, <hi>Pay that thou owest.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 18. 28. 30.</note> And as the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who pressed downe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:20306:38"/> their debters. Gods Children must <note place="margin">Esa. 58. 6.</note> shew mercy euen in asking their owne: we may not hunt with rauening affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but vse Mercy towards all, &amp; haue patience with our needy Brethren, though it be to our hinderance.</p>
            <p>Lastly, to kint vp all in a word, many poore people liue in misery, but where is our mercie that wee shew vnto them? <hi>Paul</hi> commendeth the liberality of the Churches of <hi>Macedonia, how that to their</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Gor. 8. 3.</note>
               <hi>power, yea and beyond their power they were willing,</hi> such bowels of Mercie had they toweards their poore bretheren, that wanted. In the primitiue Church <hi>they sold their Lands for the reliefe of the poore.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act 4 34 35</note>
               <hi>And the Church purposed to send releife to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 11. 29.</note>
               <hi>the bretheren which dwelt at Iudea, euen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>required thereunto,</hi> But now the Fathers of the Primitiue Church are dead, and Mercifull compassion is dead, and gone with them: They relieued the poore to their power, yea, and beyond their po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer, but now for the most part, among the Countrey people, they that are most power-full are least pitifull; and they that haue most money, haue least mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie. They sold their Lands, and gaue
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:20306:39"/> the money to the poore, but in this sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full age, some buy Lands, and begger the poore; they willingly releeued their bretheren, though not required there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto, but (alas) how hardly are men now drawen to distribute to the necis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sitie of the Saints, yea, euen they that haue great aboundance of wealth, giue what they giue so grudgingly, and ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardly, that the poore finde little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort: What wringing, oppressing, and beggering of the poore members of Christ is, that in many places which should be relieued, notwithstanding the Word of God condemning all Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mercifulnesse; and good Lawes, and Statutes enacted to the contrary. If then the Lord had a quarrell with the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> and threatned Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments against them, because they were vnmercifull, then will he not spare vs now in this Iron age of the world, when most men haue euen shut vp their bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of mercie.</p>
            <q>Nor knowledge of God in the Land.</q>
            <p>They were <hi>Israelites,</hi> how hapned it <note place="margin">1. Ioh. 3. 17.</note> then that they wanted the knowledge of God? <hi>The Lord chose them to be his owne</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 6. 7.</note>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:20306:39"/>
               <hi>people, Hee fedde them with Manna in the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 16. 15. Exo. 19 4. Deut. 32. 11. Gen. 17. 9. Deut. 11. 20. Exo. 13. 2. 12.</note>
               <hi>wildernesse, He carried them on Eagles wings out of all daunger. They had the Sacrament of Circumcision. They were commanded to haue the Law of God written vpon their house<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postes. Whether it were of their Children, or Beastes, the first borne was conscrated to God.</hi> They had the Prophets of God to teach them &amp;c. but though they had neuer so many meanes to know God, and had the word of God among them, yet the Lord heere ceargeth them by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>that there was no knowledge of God in the Land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is the ground of all Religion to know God. It were better to bee a beast then a man, and not know God: a beast is in better case then hee, when the beast dyeth, there is an end; but the Soule of man shall liue or die for euer. This is the wel-spring of all doctrine. It is won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull that the knowledge of God is not plentifull, seeing there is so much teaching.</p>
            <q>Nor knowledge of God in the Land.</q>
            <p>This striketh at the root, that there is no knowledge of God in the Land. The wicked indeed haue a naked and
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20306:40"/> bare knowledge, or lite apprehension of the knowledge of God, and descen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into the Heart, but swimming in the Braine like that euill Seruant, <hi>That knew his Maisters will, and prepared not him</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 12. 47.</note>
               <hi>selfe, neither did according to his will.</hi> Yea, the very Diuels know there is a God, <note place="margin">Mar. 1. 24. 24. Luk. 4. 41. Luk 8. 28. Act. 19. 15.</note> that there shalbe a resurrection, and a Iudgement.</p>
            <p>But there is an other knowledge of God, which carrieth the minde with a full sway to serue God: this is an holy and sanctified knowledge, discending into the Heart: of this knowledge of God, the Prophet heere speaketh: As also <hi>Esay</hi> prophesying of Christ, sayth; <hi>By his Knowledge, shall my righteous Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esa. 53. 11.</note>
               <hi>iustifie many: for hee shall beare their iniquities.</hi> Iohn Babtist <hi>Was sent to giue knowledge of this Saluation.</hi> And S. Iohn <note place="margin">Luk. 1. 77. 1. Ioh. 2. 3.</note> sayth. <hi>Hereby wee are sure that wee know him, if wee keepe his Commaundementes.</hi> Where this knowledge of God is, it bringeth foorth holy obedience to the Lawes of God; not absolute, but a care to doe them: our endeauour must be to please God, and how soeuer wee be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-wayes weake, wee shall finde it as
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:20306:40"/> a meane to purge vs from the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our nature, and to hold vs backe from sinne. They that haue this know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, are not vnfruitfull in good Workes, it worketh to their conuersi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If then thou wilt know whether thou haue this sanctified knowledge of God, it shall appeare if thou be fruite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in good workes, if thou haue not an especiall care to keepe Gods Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandementes, all thy knowledge is sinne before God.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Israelites</hi> had the knowledge of God; but God tels them, they are like the Oxe and Asse. <hi>The Oxe knoweth his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay 1. 3.</note>
               <hi>owner, and the Asse his Maisters Crib; But Israel hath not knowen: my people hath not vnderstood:</hi> and the reason was, because they were loaden with iniquitie. vers. 4. And accusing them of sinne by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremie. They haue not knowne mee</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 9. 3.</note> (saith the Lord.) And <hi>Dauid</hi> saith, <hi>They erred in their heartes, because they knew not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 95. 10</note>
               <hi>his wayes.</hi> So in like manner the Prophet <hi>Hoseas</hi> heere summoning the people of <hi>Israel</hi> to appeare before the Lord for their sinnes, chargeth them that they wanted the knowledge of God.</p>
            <pb n="74" facs="tcp:20306:41"/>
            <p>They were accused to haue no knowledge of God, because they had not a sanctified knowledge, working in them a care, and conscience to keepe Gods Commandements. And I pray God this sinne be not found among vs. I feare mee it may so. Some want the key of Knowledge, and therefore they cannot open the Chest of God, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer Manna; some are idle, and will not: and where the meane is vsed, it is wonderfull to see how the Diuell seekes to pull it away, and to keepe men in ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noraunce. Vpon the Sabaoth dayes, which are Gods great market dayes for the Soule, when <hi>Aarons</hi> golden Belles ring, and when God calleth the people to the Welles of the Water of life, It is wonderfull to see how Satan drawes them away, after the pleasures and profites of this World; and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth nothing more, then to smother Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and the knowledge of GOD: One day of seauen is ordayned of God, as the Lords great schooling day, if the Diuell can steale that day, let him take all. It is the worke of Satan to catch the Word out of our hearts. <note place="margin">Math. 13. 19</note>
            </p>
            <pb n="75" facs="tcp:20306:41"/>
            <p>And seeing that where the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God is wanting, all vices doe abound: let vs labour to haue an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall knowledge of God, lest it be truely sayd of vs, <hi>There is no knowledge of God amongst vs.</hi> And when wee see or heare the wicked boasting, and prating of God, and of his Mercies and Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses made in his Sonne Christ Iesus, let vs be bould to tell them (as heere the Prophet doth the Children of <hi>Israel)</hi> that they haue no Knowledge of God. This should teach vs to adde Practise to Knowledge.</p>
            <p>To conclude this part, let vs present our selues euery one of vs at the barre of Gods Iudgment seate, as a people indited and arrained vpon these seuerall Inditements, <hi>viz.</hi> want of Truth, want of Mercy, and the Knowledge of God, and let our owne consciences giue eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and sit as Iudges too, and wee shalbe found guilty in all; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore no remedy but speedily sue for pardon to the chiefe Iudge <hi>Christ Iesus,</hi> who is mercifull to all that truely turne to him.</p>
            <p>And thus much concerning their
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:20306:42"/> sinnes of omission. It followeth,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By Swearing, and Lying, and Killing, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">vers. 2.</note>
               <hi>Stealing, and Whoring, they breake out, and bloud toucheth Blould.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>These words are a proofe of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer accusation, wherein the Prophet proceeds to chrge the children of <hi>Israell</hi> with sinnes of Commission: and first, with swearing.</p>
            <p>Swearing is of two sorts, lawfull and vnlawfull. Againe, a lawfull Oath is of <note place="margin">Swearing.</note> two sorts, <hi>Promissorium</hi> and <hi>Assertorium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the one, we promise to doe some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing hereafter; By the other, wee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme or deny a thing to bee so, or not so: but I will not stand vpon these di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinctions.</p>
            <p>A lawfull Oath is a solemne and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest affirmation or negation of a thing lawfull and honest, by the name of God, whereby we desire him who is the onely searcher of the heart, to be a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to the truth, and a puinsher of them that sweare falsely.</p>
            <p>A lawfull Oath should haue three companions, Truth, Iudgement and <note place="margin">Iere. 4. 2.</note> Righteousnesse▪ this is proued. <hi>Thou shalt sweare, the Lord liueth, in Truth, in</hi>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:20306:42"/>
               <hi>Iudgement and in Righteousnesse.</hi> As Truth should be the ground of all our speach; so specially, when wee take the God of Truth to witnesse, wee should be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to speake nothing but the simple Truth. Wee cannot sweare lawfully, unlesse we sweare truely, our heart and tongue must goe togeather; and wee must be assured we sweare nothing but the truth: And therefore Saint <hi>Chriso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome</hi> that golden mouthed Father said well. <hi>Omnis qui iurat, ad hoc iurat, vt quod verum est loquatur.</hi> Whosoeuer sweareth, sweareth to this end, that what he spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth, be truth. The tongue and minde must sweare togeather. Wee may not equiuocate with the double hearted Papistes, whom GOD hateth, who sweare one thing, and thinke another; who haue one heart for the Prince, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other for the Pope, like <hi>Iacobs</hi> Sonnes, <hi>when they talked deceitfully with the Siche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 34. 13.</note> but heart and tongue must ioyne <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 16. Gen. 21. 23. 24. Gen. 26 31. Gen. 31. 44. Exod. 22. 8. Numb 5 19 Deut. 21. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> togeather in one truth.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he that sweareth lawfully, should sweare in Iudgement. When wee are called before a lawfull Iudge or Magistrate, to testifie a truth, which
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:20306:43"/> may not otherwayes be found out but <note place="margin">Iudg. 11 9. 10 2. Sam. 5. 3. 2. Kin. 11. 4. 2. Chro. 15. 14. 2. Chro. 34. 31.</note> by oath; or for any other lawfull cause: Then we should sweare with good dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion and aduisement; not lightly, not rashly, nor doubtfully, but with due consideration, and certaine knowledge of euery particular that wee speake of and that in matters of great importance and necessitie.</p>
            <p>A third companion of a lawfull Oath is Righteousnesse. It must be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to right and equitie, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Iustice, which giueth both to God and man his due: It must nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be against the loue of God, nor our Neighbour. It must not be an hired Oath, so to sell a mans soule to Sathan for Money; neither for feare, sauour, friendship, nor flatterie; not to doe thy Friend a pleasure, and hurt thy Foe, but in a godly zeale of the righteousnesse of the cause, and with a desire that God may be glorified in the truth.</p>
            <p>But there is an other kind of Oath, which is contrary to that trueth which should be in Gods children, and which the Prophet in this place condemneth in the children of <hi>Israell:</hi> and that is vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:20306:43"/> Swearing, as when men sweare.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 <hi>By Creatures.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 <hi>Of Custome.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 <hi>Falsely.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>None should be taken to witnesse a Truth, but onely God the Authour of Truth: God made the Creatures to serue Mans vse; not that wee should Sweare by them, and giue that honour to them, that is due to God, and so make our selues Idolaters.</p>
            <p>And the reasons are: First, because God commaundeth it as a part of his worship. <hi>Thou shalt feare the Lord thy</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 13.</note>
               <hi>God, and serue him, and shalt sweare by his name. Esay</hi> the Prophet hauing spoken of the happy estate of the Church, and the miserie of the wicked, sayth, <hi>Hee that shall blesse in the earth, shall blesse him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esa 65. 16. Psal. 63. 11. Math. 4. 10.</note>
               <hi>in the true God: and he that sweareth in the earth, shall sweare by the true God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, because it is a part of the Inuocation of God. <hi>I call God</hi> (saith the <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 9 2. Cor. 1. 23.</note> Apostle) <hi>a record to my soule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, seeing God is called a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to the conscience, wee must onely sweare by him that searcheth and try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the heart.</p>
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:20306:44"/>
            <p>Fourthly, because God in his Word expresly forbids to sweare by Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and complaineth that the <hi>Iewes</hi> had forsaken him, <hi>And swore by them that</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere 5. 7.</note>
               <hi>are no Gods.</hi> Our Sauiour Christ forbids to sweare <hi>By Heauen, for it is the Throne of God; nor by the Earth, for it is his Footestole▪</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5. 34.</note>
               <hi>neither by Jerusalem for it is the Citie of the great King; neither by thine Head, because thou canst not make one haire white or blacke.</hi> And the Apostle Saint <hi>Iames</hi> saith, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all things my brethren, Sweare not nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 5. 12.</note>
               <hi>by Heauen, nor by Earth, nor by any other Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fiftly, because this kind of Swearing brings downe the Iudgements of God vpon them that vse it. <hi>They that sweare</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amos 8. 14.</note>
               <hi>by the sinne of Samaria, that is, by Idols, and say, thy God, O Dan liueth, they shall fall, and neuer rise vp againe.</hi> And by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Zophany, The Lord threatneth to cut</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zeph. 1. 5.</note>
               <hi>off them that sweare by the Lord, and by</hi> Malcham.</p>
            <p>This serueth to reproue the Papists, and other prophane Wretches, who sweare by them that are no Gods; or ioyne God with idols; as, by God and the World, God and the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:20306:44"/> God and Fayth, and therefore forsake the Lord. Is the Virgin Saint <hi>Mary,</hi> a God? Is that patched Idoll the Masse, a God? Is your Fayth, Truth, Fire, Light, Bread, &amp;c. so many Gods? Such Swearers doe forsake the true God of Heauen, and make Creatures their gods. When the <hi>Romans</hi> sware by the fortune of <hi>Caesar,</hi> they made <hi>Caesar</hi> their God. When <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi> sware by his Throane and Kingdome, hee made his <note place="margin">Iudi. 1. 12.</note> Throane and Kingdome his God. <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycarpus</hi> to saue his life, would not sweare by the good lucke of <hi>Caesar:</hi> and shall we sweare by those that are no gods?</p>
            <p>A second kind of vnlawfull swearing is, when men sweare of custome, and in their ordinarie talke garnish their Wordes with gracelesse and needlesse Oathes, whereby they doe dishonour God: This the Lord forbiddeth. <hi>Thou shalt not take the name of the Lord thy God in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 7.</note>
               <hi>vaine, for the Lord will not hold him guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse that taketh his name in vaine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the holy Ghost saith, <hi>Accustome not thy mouth ta Swearing, for in it there are</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclesia. 23. 9, 10, 11.</note>
               <hi>many falles; neither take vp for a custome the naming of the Holy one: for thou shalt not be</hi>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:20306:45"/>
               <hi>vnpunished for such thinges.</hi> verse. 10. <hi>For as a Seruant which is oft punished, can not be without some scarre: so hee that Sweareth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclesi, 27. 14.</note>
               <hi>and nameth God</hi> (in vaine) <hi>continually, shall not be faultlesse. A man that vseth much Swearing, shall be filled with wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse, and the Plague shall not depart from his house.</hi> Our Sauiour Christ likewise saith, <hi>Let your communication be yea, yea;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 5. 27.</note>
               <hi>nay, nay: for whatsoeuer is more then these, commeth of euill.</hi> And the Apostle Saint <hi>Iames</hi> saith, <hi>Let your yea, be yea; and your</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 5. 12.</note>
               <hi>nay, nay, least you fall into condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus you see, that Swearing vpon custome in our ordinarie talke and communication, is a sinne that God will punish; it leaueth a Brand, and a Marke of Gods vengeance behinde it: the Plagues and Iudgements of God shall cleaue to him, and adide in his house that vseth it: The practise of it (as our Sauiour Christ saith) is of euill, that is, of the Diuell, because hee is the Authour of it: and (as Saint <hi>Iames</hi> saith) the end of it is damnation, Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the corruption of our times are such, that few men make conscience of it, euery Roague taketh the sacred
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:20306:45"/> name of God into his mouth, &amp; maketh it an occupation to begge by: euery Pedler and Petty-chapman, burnisheth his bad Wares, with the glorious name of GOD; and hee is accounted a chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man not worth a Chippe, that will not sweare, to deceiue those that deale with him: neuer was ordinarie and idle Swearing more in request amongst the <hi>Iewes,</hi> then now among vs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</p>
            <p>The last and highest degree of Swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is Periurie, or swearing falsely. Some make a difference betweene them, as Periurie in that which is to come; and forswearing in falsely affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, or denying a thing to be so, or not so; neuerthelesse the one is often taken for the other.</p>
            <p>This Periurie or false Swearing, is an horrible sinne: the Lord hath expresly forbidden it in his Law. <hi>You shall not</hi> (saith hee) <hi>Sweare by my name falsly neither</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leui. 19. 12.</note>
               <hi>shalt thou defile the name of thy God. I am the Lord. The flying Booke of Gods Curses shall enter into the house of him that falsely Sweareth by my name</hi> (saith the Lord,) <hi>and it shall remaine in the middest of his house,</hi>
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:20306:46"/>
               <hi>and shall consume it, with the timber thereof, and the stones thereof.</hi> By his Prophet <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 5. 2. 3. 4. Iere. 5. 2.</note> hee reproueth the <hi>Iewes</hi> for this sinne. Yea, the Lord <hi>Hateth and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them that gweare falsely.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zach. 8. 17.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And least we should thinke that God would so haue done with them, he saith, <hi>They shall not dwell in his Tabernacle, nor</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 15. 2.</note>
               <hi>rest in his holy Mountaine.</hi> They shalbe excluded out of the holy Cittie; <hi>And from the Tree of Life; and they shall haue</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 21. 8.</note>
               <hi>their part in the Lake which burneth with fire and brimstone: which is the second death.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 22 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How dangerous and damnable a sinne Periurie or false-Swearing is, it may appeare by many Reasons; especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally because they sinne,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Against God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Against them selues.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Against their neighbours.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>First, they sinne against God, because when they speake against the Trueth, they speake against God, and take part with the Diuell: and therefore God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <note place="margin">Pro. 6. 16. 17. 19.</note> them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, because they doe not onely turne the Trueth of God into a Lie, but also make God a party in their sinne, &amp;
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:20306:46"/> take the name of the God of Truth, to witnesse a lye.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, because they commit high treason against God; for as when an earthly King committeth the great Seale of his Kingdome to the custodie of some one man; If hee to whom the same is committed, should therewith seale Letters of Treason, hee might iustly bee condemned for a Traytour: So, seeing the glorious Name of God is committed to vs, as a Seale, to testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and confirme the Trueth; as if any man abuse that blessed Seale of the sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred <note place="margin">Heb. 6. 16.</note> Name of the King of Heauen, to confirme a Lie withall, hee committeth high Treason against the Maiestie of God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, Periurie, or False-swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, is an horrible sinne: because For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sworne wretches do sinne against them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues.</p>
            <p>First, in that they doe giue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues vp to Satan, by their Periurie, they renounce God, and all the sweete Promises conteyned in the Booke of God, whereupon they lay their hand, and bring downe vpon their owne
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:20306:47"/> heads, all the fearefull woes and curses contained in the same Booke; when a false-swearer reacheth out his hand to the Booke, hee giueth it to the Diuell; kissing the Booke, he kisseth the Diuell; when hee bringeth meate or drinke to his mouth with that hand, hee feedeth himselfe with the hand of the Diuell; nay, rather he remaineth a Diuell in car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, then a man.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they doe sinne against themselues, because they make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues worse then Sathan; <hi>For though hee be a lier, and the father of lies,</hi> yet wee doe <note place="margin">Iohn. 8. 44.</note> not read, that hee durst euer presume to seale his lies with the name of God: But the filthy for-sworne Catife is one degree beyonde the Diuell, for hee is both a lyer, and also dare without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence, feare, or trembling, take Gods name into his mouth, to confirme a lye withall; which Sathan neuer durst doe. <note place="margin">Iam 2. 19.</note> There is no infirnall Diuell that euer cast himselfe into condemnation for Money; but some Periured persons there are, who readily cast Soule and Body into destruction for a little Pelfe and Drosse of this world; <hi>Which</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:20306:47"/>
               <hi>one day shall witnesse against them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 5. 3.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, it is a dangerous and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable sinne, because for-sworne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons sinne also against their neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours; whom they hurt or offend by their Periurie. First, if it be in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique place of Iustice, hee sinneth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Iudge, in causing him, by his Periurie, to giue vnrighteous sentence; Iudgement is peruerted thereby, and a bad cause passeth for good. Secondly, hee sinneth against the Iurie, in causing them to giue vp a false verdict. Yea, in a word, his Periurie sometimes pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uayleth so farre against his Neighbour, that thereby hee carrieth away Lands and Goods wrongfully; and sometimes putteth a true mans Necke into the Halter, and casteth downe his owne soule into Hell.</p>
            <p>This sinne is further aggrauated also, by consideration of the matter; If it be in a matter for the glory of God, the sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of mens Soules, the life of Man, or his state of liuing, or the publique good of the Church or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth; hee that sweareth falsey in such <note place="margin">2. Sam. 21. 2. Ios. 9. 18.</note> things, his sinne is most horrible. Last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:20306:48"/> this sinne is increased, when Periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red persons doe not onely take Gods name to witnesse a Lye, but also curse themselues, if it be not true which they affirme, whereas in their owne consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence they know it to be a Lie. They will curse themselues to Hell, &amp; protest they will forsake God, if it be not so as they say; they will desire God to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found them, and pray God they may neuer come to Heauen if it be not thus, and thus; with many such like detesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble imprecations, as would make a good mans heart quake to heare them Such beastly people doe prouoke God to his face to take vengeance on them: and if the Lord in his Iustice, should take them at their wordes, how miserable were their state?</p>
            <p>Let vs then (beloued) vse the Name of God reuerently; and when wee are called to take a lawfull Oath, let vs doe it in Trueth, Iudgement, and Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse: let vs not accustome our selues to sweare by Creatures, nor to take Gods Name into our mouthes in our ordinarie talke: and be it farre from vs that wee should presume to seale a
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:20306:48"/> Lye with the blessed Name of God, and so sinne against his sacred Maiestie, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our selues, and our soules, and against our neighbours, and make our selues as guilty of swearing, in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est degree, as euer did the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> &amp; so bring Gods fearefull Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments vpon our heads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(And Lying:)</hi> Next to Swearing, hee <note place="margin">Lying.</note> chargeth them with Lying, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by prooueth, that there is no trueth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them: Because Swearing and Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the most part are Inmates, and dwell both vnder one roofe, and walke <note place="margin">Math. 26. 70. 72.</note> hand in hand, like the Thiefe and the Receiuer: or as the Vsurer and the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, (for take a Swearer, and hee is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly a Lyer:) therefore the Prophet heere placeth them next togeather.</p>
            <p>A Lye, is a voluntarie speaking of that which is vntrue, with a purpose to deceiue. S. <hi>Augustine</hi> maketh mention of eight kinds of Lyes: but others con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract them into three sorts.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:20306:49"/>
               <item>1 A Merry
<list>
                     <item>Lie,
<list>
                           <item>Sport, for Gaine, Spight,
<list>
                                 <item>Delight. to Profit. Hurt.</item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2 An Officious</item>
               <item>3 A Malicions</item>
            </list>
            <p>A Merry or Iesting Lye; when a man of purpose telles a Lie, to delight, and make them sport that heare him. Some goe about to cleare this kind of lying not to be sinne. But our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Christ saith, <hi>That of euerie idle word that men shall speake, they shall giue account</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 12. 36</note>
               <hi>at the day of Iudgement.</hi> If wee must giue account for euery Idle word, before that great Iudge Iesus Christ; then much more of Idle Lyes. And if the Apostle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would not haue vs so much as speake <hi>Of any filthinesse, nor foolish talking, nor iesting, which are thinges</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 5, 4.</note>
               <hi>not comely; but rather giuing of thankes.</hi> Then why should Christians turne Fooles, to make others sport, or deuise iesting Lyes, to make men laugh, <hi>But rather take heede that their speech be alwayes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 4. 6.</note>
               <hi>gratious, and powdred with salt,</hi> and such as is good to the vse of edifying, and that it may minister (not gaine) but grace vnto the hearers.</p>
            <pb n="91" facs="tcp:20306:49"/>
            <p>The second is an officious Lie, when a man tels a Lie for duties sake, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to gaine good to others, by deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring them from death or danger, or procuring profite to themselues. So the Mid-wiues of <hi>Egipt,</hi> by a Lie, saued the Children of the <hi>Hebrewes</hi> aliue, <note place="margin">Exod. 1. 19.</note>
               <hi>Rahab</hi> by her Lie preserued the Spies <note place="margin">Iosh. 5.</note> of Gods people. And <hi>Michal</hi> by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Lie, saued her Husband <hi>Dauids</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 19. 14. 17.</note> life. Though some Writers, as <hi>Origen,</hi> and <hi>Hierom,</hi> and others, seeke shiftes to excuse this kind of Lying in good men, yet they are deceiued; for euery Lie is sinne: yea, though a man would pretend to make a Lie for the glory of God, or the safeguard of a mans life; yet wee may not doe euill, that good <note place="margin">Rom. 3. 8.</note> may come of it. And therefore Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> saith concerning the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiues Lie, made for the preseruation of the liues of the young Children of the <hi>Ebrewes,</hi> That their feare of God, tender care, and carefull compassion, mercifully to spare the Infants, plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed God; but their Lie pleased not God. And if (as the same Father saith) it bee not lawfull to Lie, though it
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:20306:50"/> could be to the prayse of God; much lesse then for the sauing of a mans life. <hi>Iob</hi> therefore reprooued a Lie in his Friendes, though it tended to defende the Lord: <hi>Will you speake Wickedly</hi> (saith <note place="margin">Iob. 13. 7.</note> hee) <hi>for Gods defence, and talke deceitfully for his cause?</hi> To say then that some Lies are good, is as much to say, some Sinnes are good. Gods Law is Truth, &amp; whatsoeuer is contrarie to the Truth, is contrarie to Gods Law: But euerie Lie is contrarie to the Trueth, therefore euery Lie is contrarie to Gods Law. True it is that one sinne is worse then another; so is one Lie worse then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other: but euery Lie is sinne. God and Satan are two contraries; so are Trueth and Lying: Truth is from God, and Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is from the Diuell. Though God can doe all things; yet hee cannot Lie, because it is contrary to his nature: but <note place="margin">Tit. 1. 2.</note> when Satan lyeth, hee speaketh of his <note place="margin">Heb 6. 8. Ioh 8. 44.</note> owne.</p>
            <p>Let no man then iustifie that which God condemneth; but let all those that loue the GOD of Truth, and hate the Diuell, loue Truth, and loath all manner of Lies.</p>
            <pb n="93" facs="tcp:20306:50"/>
            <p>Againe, as some goe about to make good this kind of Lying, which tendes to the preseruation of life, and to gaine good to others: So there is some a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst vs, that say, it is no sinne to Lie for aduantage, thereby to bring pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite to themselues, or keepe togeather that which they haue, alleadging the example of <hi>Iacob,</hi> who by his Mothers <note place="margin">Gen. 27. 19.</note> counsell, made a lye to his Father <hi>Izhak,</hi> thereby to gaine his Blessing. They might as well say that Adulterie and Murther are no sinnes, because <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> a man after GODS owne heart, committed them both. Wee must liue by Lawes, not by Examples: The falles of Gods Children are mentioned in the Booke of life, for our comfort and instruction; not for our Imitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Wee are to follow the Saintes no farther, then they follow the Lord. So also <hi>Gehazei</hi> made a Lie to <hi>Naaman</hi> the <hi>Syrian,</hi> thereby to make a gaine to <note place="margin">2. King. 5. 22. 27.</note> himselfe: but it proued a madde kinde of gaine; for hee gained the Leprosie to himselfe and his posteritie. Such there bee many now adayes, who make no conscience to Lie for aduantage; yea,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:20306:51"/> if they haue a Child or a Seruant that can Lie, to gaine them a Groat, oh, that is a Child alone, that is a Seruant alone: But they doe little consider that such gaine gotten by Lying, brings a curse vpon all that a man hath.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> Lied for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uantage, thereby purposing to saue to <note place="margin">Act. 5. 3. 8.</note> themselues halfe the price of their land; but they payde deare for their Lying, they made but a sory match of it. But though <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> were ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie hundred yeares agoe stricken dead by Gods iust Iudgement, for this kind of Lying, yet there is still some of their brood amongst vs. Let a Poore man make his moane to the Rich for maintenance or reliefe, their answere (for the most part) is readier then their Almes, <hi>GOD helpe thee,</hi> I haue it not for thee; and so looking vp their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, they make no conscience to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie the Lord, who hath giuen them enough both for themselues, and the Poore.</p>
            <p>Were it not a iust thing with God, to part such Peasants and their Pelfe, by some sodaine Iudgement or other.
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:20306:51"/> Take heed then, learne not thy tongue to Lie for aduantage, though thereby thou couldest gaine, or saue a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to thy selfe. Euery Lie is sinne, and the reward of sinne is death. And, <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 23. Mat. 16. 26.</note>
               <hi>What shall it profit a man to winne all the World, and to loose his owne Soule.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third and worst kind of Lying, is a malicious or pernitious Lie, procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from a corrupt minde, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the hurt of others. So <hi>Potiphar</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 39. 14. 15. 17. 18.</note> his wife be-lyed <hi>Ioseph.</hi> Such a Lie the false-witnesses testified against <hi>Naboth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Kin. 21. 13.</note> which cost him his Land, and his Life too. So the two Elders be-lied <hi>Susanna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 13. 36. 37. 38.</note> and set her hard for her life. Such a Lie also <hi>Haman</hi> told against <hi>Mordocai</hi> and <note place="margin">Ester. 3. 8.</note> the <hi>Iewes.</hi> And the Pharisies against Christ. No man was euer so impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, <note place="margin">Math 9. 3. Mat 12, 24.</note> as to goe about to excuse, much lesse to defende this kinde of Lying. Whether then it bee a merry, an offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, or malicious Lie, though you turne the fayrest side of it outward, and make the best of it, yet if it be a Lie, it is sinne, and the worke of Satan, and that for these reasons.</p>
            <p>First, because God forbids all kindes
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:20306:52"/> of Lies without distinction. <hi>Thou shalt</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leui. 19 16.</note>
               <hi>not</hi> (saith the Lord) <hi>walke about with Tales among thy people, &amp;c. I am the Lord. Ʋse</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 7. 13.</note>
               <hi>not to make any manner of Lie, for the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stome thereof is not good. Dauid</hi> saith, <hi>That God shall destroy them that speake Lies.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 5. 6.</note> Our Sauiour Christ sayth (without making difference of Lyes) <hi>That Satan</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 8. 44.</note>
               <hi>is a Lyer, and the Father thereof.</hi> The A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle <hi>Paul</hi> would haue vs cast off Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>And speake trueth euery man to his Neighbours: for wee are members one of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 3. 9.</note>
               <hi>another.</hi> And againe, <hi>Lie not one to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, seeing that you haue put off the Old man with his Workes: Who will not make conscience of Murther, because God forbids it?</hi> And seeing God commaundeth to speake Truth, and forbids all Lying, thou shouldest not Lie, if thou couldest gaine an house-full of Gold by it; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause God forbids it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, because God and good men hate and abhorre it, and therefore it is twice repeated among those sinnes which God hateth. And againe, <hi>The Lying lippes are abhomination to the Lord.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 16. 19. Prou 12. 22.</note> And therefore the holy Ghost prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a Thiefe, before a Lyer: a Thiefe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:20306:52"/> is better then a man that is accustomed to lye: <hi>But they both shall haue destruction</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 20. 24.</note>
               <hi>to heritage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as God abhorreth all Lying, so good men also hate it. <hi>A righteous man</hi> (saith <hi>Salomon) hateth Lying wordes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 13. 5. Eccle. 25. 2.</note>
               <hi>but the wicked causeth slaunder, and shame. Dauid</hi> would not suffer a Lier to dwell in his House, nor tarrie in his sight. <hi>There shall no Deceitfull person</hi> (saith hee) <hi>dwell within mine House; Hee that telleth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 101. 7.</note>
               <hi>Lies shall not remaine in my sight.</hi> And therefore as <hi>Salomon</hi> prayed against Lying, so let all Gods Children doe the <note place="margin">Pro. 30. 8.</note> like.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, because Lying hurteth them that vse it, It maketh good men wearie of their companie: It impayreth <note place="margin">Iere. 9. 2. 3.</note> a mans credite, because hee that accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stometh his tongue to Lie, shall not bee beleeued at all: And therefore <hi>Demetri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> being asked what a Lyer gayneth by Lying? he answered, <hi>That hee shall not be</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 10. 23. 25.</note>
               <hi>beleeued when hee speaketh trueth.</hi> A Lie is a wicked shame in a man. And againe, <hi>The conditions of Liers are vnhonest, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle 41. 17.</note>
               <hi>their shame is euer with them.</hi> verse 25. And therefore Gods Children should
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:20306:53"/> be ashamed of lying. The very care of a mans credite should make him to leaue it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, because it brings temporall Iudgements with it. <hi>A False witnesse</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 19. 5.</note> (saith <hi>Salomon) shall not be vnpunished; and hee that speaketh Lies, shall not escape.</hi> The <hi>Gibeonites</hi> for making a Lie to <hi>Iosuah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ios. 9. 6. 23.</note> were accursed, and made slaues to the <hi>Israelites. Gehazi</hi> for making a Lie to <note place="margin">2. Kin. 5. 22.</note>
               <hi>Elisha,</hi> was punished with Leprosie. <hi>Haman</hi> for his Lie was hanged. <hi>Ananias</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ester. 7. 10. Act. 5. 5. 10.</note> and <hi>Saphira</hi> for their lying, felt the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie hand of Gods vengeance by so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine destruction. By the Prophet <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheas</hi> the Lord threatneth destruction against the people for their crueltie, and lying. <hi>Hee will make them sicke in smi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi>
               <note place="margin">Micha. 6. 12. 13.</note>
               <hi>them, and desolate. &amp;c.</hi> And heere he telleth the children of <hi>Israel,</hi> that the Lord hath a controuersie with them, <hi>And that their Land shall mourne, &amp;c.</hi> for lying, and other their sinnes.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, if this sinne of Lying bee not repented of in this life, it bringeth at last, eternall destruction both of body and soule; <hi>For the Fearefull, and Vnbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, and the Abhominable, &amp; Murtherers,</hi>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:20306:53"/>
               <hi>and Whore-mongers, and Sorcerers, and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 21. 8. 27.</note>
               <hi>and all Lyers, shall haue their part in the Lake which burneth with Fire and Brim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stone; which is the second death. And they shall not enter into the holy and heauenly Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rusalem; but they shall be shut out with Dogges, Enchanters, Whore-mongers, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 22. 15.</note>
               <hi>and Idolaters. God will destroy them that speake Lyes.</hi> And the Apostle sayth, <note place="margin">Psal. 5. 6.</note>
               <hi>That the Law is not giuen vnto a righteous man, but vnto the lawlesse, and disobedient,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Tim. 1. 9. 10.</note>
               <hi>to the vngodly, and the sinner, to the vnholy, and to the prophane, to murtherers of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers, to manslayers, to whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, to buggerers, manstealers, to lyers, to the periured &amp;c.</hi> It must needs be a great offence, that causeth a Father to disin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herite his Sonne: but such a sinne is liing, that it seperateth them that vse it, from the presence and fauour of the God of Truth, depriueth them of his Kingdome, and maketh them slaues to Satan.</p>
            <p>Lastly, because it is a diuelish sinne, both in respect of the beginning, the practise, and end of it.</p>
            <p>First, because Satan told the first Lie. <hi>And when hee speaketh a Lie, hee speaketh of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 4. Ioh. 8. 44.</note>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:20306:54"/>
               <hi>his owne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, because they that vse it, are of the Diuell: for as <hi>Peter</hi> was knowne to bee of <hi>Galilee,</hi> because his speach was as the <hi>Galileans;</hi> so Liers are knowne to bee of the Diuell, because their speach is alike.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, because all Lies shall be pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nished with the Diuell (as you haue heard) vnlesse they repent: Let all Gods Children then cast away lying, because God forbids it, God and good men hate and abhorre it, it hurteth them that vse it: it brings Iudgements temporall and eternall, and is a diuelish sinne, both in respect of the beginning, practise, and end of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(And Killing.)</hi> This sheweth more particularly, that there was no mercy <note place="margin">Killing.</note> among them; but crueltie, and Killing.</p>
            <p>Killing, is also of two sorts: Lawfull, and vnlawfull.</p>
            <p>The Magistrate may lawfully Kill, or put to death malefactors; because he beareth not the Sword for naught: <note place="margin">Rom. 13. 4.</note>
               <hi>For hee is the Minister of God, to take vengeance on him that doeth euill.</hi> The Lord also in his Law approueth, and
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:20306:54"/> commandeth this, <hi>Whosoeuer Killeth any</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 20. 9. 10. Leui. 24. 17. Deut. 19. 16. 17. Deut. 22. 22. Psal. 101. 8.</note>
               <hi>person, the Iudge shall slea the Murtherer, through Witnesses. I will</hi> (saith <hi>Dauid) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy all the wicked in the land.</hi> Where wee may see <hi>Dauids</hi> authoritie, as hee was a King, hee voweth to God, as a thing acceptable to him, to destroy, and roote out all the Wicked: and therefore hee also charged his sonne <hi>Salomon,</hi> to put <note place="margin">1. King. 2. 5, 6. 28. 31. 32,</note>
               <hi>Ioab</hi> the Murtherer to death: Which may serue as a warrant to Magistrates, (notwithstanding the commandement) to punish Malefactours with death. Besides this, the Commaundement was giuen to man; but the Magistrates <note place="margin">2 Chro. 19. 6.</note> killing, it is not mans killing, it is Gods action, God putteth the Sword into his hand: hee executes not the Iudgements <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> of man, but of the Lord, and he is Gods minister applying himselfe for the same thing.</p>
            <p>They are then greatly deceiued, who thinke it not lawfull to put any man to death, for any cause, but would haue all Mercie, and no Iustice. Let <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> answeare them in a word. <hi>Hee that iustifieth the wicked, and hee that condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 17. 8.</note>
               <hi>the iust, euen they both are abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:20306:55"/>
               <hi>to the Lord.</hi> So <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Achab,</hi> by their foolish pittie, prouoked God to <note place="margin">1. Sam. 15. 3. 9 11. 18. 1. Kin. 20. 42.</note> wrath, in sparing of those, whom God would haue put to death.</p>
            <p>But there is also an vnlawfull kinde of Killing, which the Prophet in this place, condemneth in the Children of <hi>Israel,</hi> which is practised specially in three things; Heart. Tongue, &amp; Hand: <note place="margin">Psal. 142 2. 3. 4.</note> against all which, <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth.</p>
            <p>Killing of the Heart, is the fountaine: the Tongue, and Hand, are instruments. <hi>The Lord saw that the imaginations of mans</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 8. 12.</note>
               <hi>Heart <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> euill.</hi> And our Sauiour Christ saith, <hi>That those things which proceed out of the Mouth, come from the Heart; and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 15. 18. 19.</note>
               <hi>they defile the man: For out of the Heart, commeth euill thoughts, murther, adulteries, &amp;c.</hi> It is a bloody Heart, that maketh a bloody Man. <hi>Saul</hi> was a murtherer in Heart and Will, when hee hunted after <note place="margin">1. Sam. 18. 11. 1 Sam. 19. 2. &amp; 20. 31. 33.</note>
               <hi>Dauid,</hi> and carried a bloody minde a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst him. So was <hi>Haman</hi> a murtherer in Heart, though not in effect. And the <note place="margin">Ester 3. 6. Mat 26. 3 4. Mar. 14. 1. Luk. 2. 2. Ioh. 8. 59.</note>
               <hi>Iewes</hi> were murtherers, when they went about to kill Christ. When a man carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a killing affection, then he is a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, and a right limme of the Diuell.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:20306:55"/>
            <p>The bloody-minded <hi>Seminaries</hi> that are sent ouer into <hi>England,</hi> and our late Gun-powder traytors, and the rest of that damnable and Popish brood, who haue from time to time, plotted most inhumane and bloody attempts against the Lords annoynted, and the state of this Realme, though the Lord of his meere mercie towardes vs (his Name be therefore euer blessed) hath frustrated their filthy and inhumane attemptes, and brought the Wheele vpon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues; yet are they accursed Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers before God: their blood bee vpon themselues.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Tongue is an instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherewith the Heart killeth; and it hath also many weapons to kill with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, especially sixe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Counsell.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Commaundement.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>False witnesse.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Silence.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>Slander.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>Backbyting.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>St. <hi>Iames</hi> describeth the properties of a Killing tongue. <hi>It is Fire, yea a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iam. 3. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10.</note>
               <hi>world of Wickednesse, it defileth the whole</hi>
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:20306:56"/>
               <hi>body, and setteth on fire the course of Nature: and is set on fire of Hell.</hi> 7. <hi>For the whole nature of Beastes, and of Birdes, and of cree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping things, and things of the Sea, is tamed, and hath been tamed of the nature of man.</hi> 8. <hi>But the Tongue can no man tame, it is an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly euill, full of deadly poyson. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, though the Heathens know not God, yet they know this well enough, and therefore <hi>Esope</hi> bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing sent by his Maister to the Market to buy the best and worst Meate, hee bought all Tongues; affirming that no flesh was better then a good Tongue, and none worse then a badde Tongue: It is a killing and destroying weapon, and cutteth deceitfully like a sharpe <note place="margin">Psal. 52. 2. 4</note> Rasor. <hi>The double Tongue</hi> (saith the sonne of <hi>Syrach) hath destroyed many that were at peace; it hath disquieted many, and driuen</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 28. 13. to 22.</note>
               <hi>them from nation to nation; strong Cities hath it broken downe, and ouerthrowne the houses of great men. The stroke of the Rodde maketh markes in the flesh; but the stroke of the Tongue breaketh the bones.</hi> 17. <hi>The tongue hath sinne more then the Sword.</hi> 28. <hi>The death thereof is an euill death, Hell were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then such one.</hi> A killing Tongue is
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:20306:56"/> compared to a Serpents tongue. It is compared to an Arrow, and a sharpe <note place="margin">Psal. 140. 3.</note> Sword: Nay, it is worse then any sharpe <note place="margin">Iere. 9. 8. Iob. 5. 15. Psal 64. 3. Psal. 59. 7. Psal. 120. 4.</note> Sword, or Arrow; for the Sword, and Arrow, onely wound, or kill the Body; but a badde Tongue also hurteth or killeth a mans estimation and good name. A man may beare off, or flie from the stroke of the Sword, or shot of the Arrow; but there is no way to escape a klling Tongue. The woundes which the Sword, or Arrow giueth, may bee healed; but no Salue can cure the wounds of a badde Tongue. The Sword or Arrow kill, or hurt none, but those that are at hand, or not farre off: but a murthering Tongue, woundeth and killeth those often, that are many miles distant.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that the Tongue is such a perilous weapon, that there is no medling with it, let vs onely pray a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it, as <hi>Dauid</hi> did. <hi>Heare my voyce (O God) in my prayer, preserue my life from</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psa. 64. 1. 2. 3 Iob. 5. 21.</note>
               <hi>feare of the enemie. Hide mee from the conspiracie of the Wicked, and from the rage of the workers of Iniquitie, which haue what their Tongue like a Sword, and shot foorth</hi>
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:20306:57"/>
               <hi>their Arrowes bitter words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Hand is also an instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wherewith the Heart killeth, sometimes by the ministerie of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. So <hi>Dauid</hi> killed <hi>Ʋrias.</hi> So <hi>Ahab</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam 11. 6. 14 15. 1. Kin. 21. 7. 10.</note> and <hi>Iezabel</hi> killed <hi>Naboth.</hi> So <hi>Herod</hi> killed all the male Children that were in <hi>Beth-lem, and in all the coastes thereof;</hi> which is to bee considered of such bad men, as when they cause others to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit Murther, thinke themselues inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent: but let all such know, that they are Murtherers, though they vse others as their instruments.</p>
            <p>Sometimes also the Hand killeth by withholding or taking away things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nessarie from them that haue need: For hee that withholdeth or taketh away the meanes whereby life is preserued, hee is a Murtherer.</p>
            <p>And therefore the Lord in the Law, saith, <hi>Thou shalt not oppresse an Hired ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant, that is needy and poore, &amp;c. But thou</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 2. 16. Deut. 24. 14. 15.</note>
               <hi>shalt giue him his Hire for his day, neither shall the Sunne goe downe vpon it, for hee is poore, and therewith sustayneth his life, least hee cry against thee vnto the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> And hence it is, that the Lord by his
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:20306:57"/> Prophet <hi>Esay</hi> chargeth the vnmercifull <note place="margin">Esay 1. 15.</note> and oppressing <hi>Iewes,</hi> that their Hands are full of Blood. And <hi>Iesus the sonne of Syrach</hi> saith, <hi>Who so bringeth an Offering of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccles. 34, 21. 22. 23.</note>
               <hi>the goods of the Poore, doth as one that sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficeth the Sonne before the Fathers eyes.</hi> 21. <hi>The Bread of the needfull, is the life of the Poore; hee that defrawdeth him thereof, is a Murtherer.</hi> 22. <hi>Hee that taketh away his Neighbours Liuing slayeth him: and hee that defrawdeth the Labourer of his Hire, is a Bloodshedder.</hi> Thus the greedie cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throates of the World kill their Brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, by suffering poore Soules to stand crying at their doores, without comfort; of whom St. <hi>Augustine</hi> saith, <hi>Si non pauisti, occidisti.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others, by their immoderate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauncing of the price of thinges, rac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Rentes, depopulating of Townes, and turning out the Poore to begge, and taking away the meanes of their maintenaunce, become guiltie of their blood.</p>
            <p>Sometimes also the Hand Killeth by actuall Murther, committed vpon the body of another. <hi>So Kain killed his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4 8. 2. Sam. 3. 27 2. Sam. 20. 10.</note>
               <hi>brother Habel. So Ioab killed Abner, and</hi>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:20306:58"/>
               <hi>Amasa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And lastly, when a man layeth vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent hands on himselfe; <hi>So Saul and his Armour bearer fell vpon their Swords, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 31. 4. 5. 2. Sam. 17, 23. Mat. 27. 5.</note>
               <hi>killed themselues. Thus also Ahitophel, and Iudas, hanged themselues.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hauing thus shewed you how many wayes this sinne may bee committed; now it remaineth to shew you, that this Capitall sinne <hi>(Killing)</hi> is most horrible and abhominable, and that for these speciall reasons:</p>
            <p>First, <hi>Because God forbids it in his Law. Yea, the very Infidels abhorre it.</hi> If there <note place="margin">Exod. 20. 13 Deut. 5. 17. Math. 5. 21. Rom. 13. 9. Act. 28 4.</note> were no more but this, it were enough to make any Christian tremble to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaue so much as an intent to commit it.</p>
            <p>Secondly, because it is a crying sinne: when <hi>Kain</hi> had killed his brother <hi>Habel,</hi> God told him, <hi>That the voyce of his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Blood, cryed vnto him from the Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 10.</note> Neuer was droppe of Innocent blood shedde, but it cryed for vengeance: and therefore <hi>Iob</hi> sayth, That the Earth can <note place="margin">Iob. 16. 18.</note> not couer Blood.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, because it is an accursed <note place="margin">Deut. 21 9.</note> sinne.</p>
            <pb n="109" facs="tcp:20306:58"/>
            <p> First, it bringeth the Curse of God <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 8. 11.</note> vpon the Murtherer, and maketh him carry a guiltie Conscience: as wee see in <hi>Kain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, it bringes a Curse vpon a <note place="margin">2. Sam. 3. 29</note> mans posteritie.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Magistrate is accursed, <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12. 10</note> that leaueth it vnpunished.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, it defileth the Earth, and <note place="margin">1. Kin. 2. 31. 33. Ier. 48. 10. Iud. 20. 13. 44. Gen. 4. 12. Ioh. 8. 44. 1. Ioh. 3. 12.</note> maketh it accursed.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, because it is also a diuelish sinne. It proceedes from the Diuell, <hi>Who was a Murtherer from the beginning.</hi> Therefore when thou seest a Murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, thou seest the very Image and Picture of the Diuell. <hi>Kain</hi> the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer, was of the Diuell; his Murther, was the worke of the Diuell. <hi>After that</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 16. 14.</note>
               <hi>the Spirit of the Lord was departed from Saul, and an euill Spirit sent of the Lord vexed him. Saul</hi> thencefoorth hunted <hi>Dauid</hi> for his life, to Kill him. The two possessed with Diuels, were so fierce, that no man might goe by that way, (such a delight they had to Kill men.) Satan no sooner entred into <hi>Iudas,</hi> but <note place="margin">Math. 8. 28. Luk. 22. 3. 4. Ioh. 13. 2.</note> presently he sought Christes blood, to haue him put to death. Therefore bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:20306:59"/> Papists, who practise to kill &amp; poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son Kinges and Princes, are of the Diuell, and ledde by the spirit of the Diuell: Those Popish Frogges whom <hi>Anti-christ</hi> sendeth to stirre vp hurly-burlyes among Princes▪ and hide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selues, croaking in corners, to doe mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe, came out of the mouth of the <note place="margin">Apo. 16. 13. 14.</note> Dragon, the Beast, and false Prophet. See then with what spirit the <hi>Seminaries,</hi> and other bloody minded Papistes are ledde, who practise nothing but Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering and Poysoning of Christian Princes; their worke is of the Diuell, and they are guided by his spirit. The Spirit of God is otherwise affected; for when <hi>Dauid</hi> might haue slaine <hi>Saul,</hi> at two seuerall times hee would not, but <note place="margin">1. Sam. 24. 5. 6 7. 1. Sam. 26. 8. 11.</note> sayd, <hi>The Lord keepe mee from doing that thing to my Maister▪ the Lords Annoynted;</hi> yea, hee was touched in heart, because hee had cut off the Lappe which was on <hi>Sauls</hi> Carment. If <hi>Dauids</hi> heart smote him, for touching the Kings Garment, What shall become of them that would pierce the Kinges Heart? Neuer did any Heretiques maintaine Treason, &amp; Murthering of Princes but the Papists.
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:20306:59"/>
               <hi>Touch not mine Annoynted,</hi> (said <hi>God:)</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal, 105. 15.</note> Nay Kill Gods Annoynted, say the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists. If the Pope were <hi>Peters</hi> successor, <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2. 13. 17.</note> then would hee teach the people to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour Kinges and Princes, and submit themselues to them, as <hi>Peter</hi> did. But the Pope sendes out his blood sucking Shauelinges to kill Christian Princes; and therfore he is not <hi>Peters</hi> successour, but hee is of his Father the Diuell, who was a Murtherer from the beginning.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, because God hath a Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uersie with the people for this sinne, and will haue account of all the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent blood that is shedde; and will bee auenged on them that shedde it. <hi>I will</hi> (saith the Lord) <hi>require your blood wherein</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 9. 5 6.</note>
               <hi>your liues are: at the handes of euery Beast will I require it, and at the hand of man, euen at the hand of mans brother will I require the life of man. Who so sheddeth mans blood, by man shall his blood be shedde; for in the image of God, hath he made man.</hi> And the Lord God in his Law commaundeth, <hi>That hee that killeth any man, shall be</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leui. 24. 17. Num. 35. 16 17 18. 19 20.</note>
               <hi>put to death.</hi> And also hee forbids that any shall sell the blood of the Murde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>You shall not</hi> (saith hee) <hi>take any</hi>
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:20306:60"/>
               <hi>recompence for the life of the Murtherer,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 35. 31</note>
               <hi>which is worthy to die, but hee shall bee put to death.</hi> And our Sauiour Christ said to <hi>Peter, That all which take the Sword, shall</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 52.</note>
               <hi>perish with the Sword. Ioab</hi> slue <hi>Abner</hi> and <hi>Amasa, Absolon,</hi> and others; and <note place="margin">2. Sam 3. 27 2. Sam. 20. 9. 10. 2. Kin. 2 32. 33. 1. Kin. 18. 4. 1. Kin. 21. 8, 10, 17.</note> at last, by Gods iust iudgement himselfe was slaine. <hi>Iesabel</hi> caused the Prophets of God to be slaine, and procured <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths</hi> death: but at last, she was cast out at a Window, her blood was sprinkled vpon the Wall, and vpon the Horses; and shee was troden vnder foote, and the Dogges eate her flesh, so that no <note place="margin">2. Kin. 9. 33, 35, 36.</note> more was found of her but the Skull, and the Feete, and the Palmes of her Hands. <hi>Herod Agrippa,</hi> hauing perse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted the Christians, killed <hi>Iames</hi> the <note place="margin">Act. 12. 2, 3, 23.</note> brother of <hi>Iohn</hi> with the Sword, and put <hi>Peter</hi> in Prison &amp;c. at last by Gods iust iudgement, <hi>Hee was eaten of Wormes, and gaue vp the Ghost.</hi> And though the Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therer sometimes die in his Bed, yet, as <hi>Goliath</hi> was slaine with his owne sword; <note place="margin">1. sam. 17. 51</note> so the Murtherers owne Conscience shall wound him, and continually tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment him. Such a curse fell vpon <hi>Kain,</hi> his Conscience after hee had killed his
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:20306:60"/> brother <hi>Habel, That hee thought euery one</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 14.</note>
               <hi>that saw him, would sley him.</hi> It is written of <hi>Herod Antipas,</hi> that after he had behea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>John Baptist,</hi> hee carried such an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cusing <note place="margin">Mat. 14. 10.</note> Conscience, that hee thought euery Bush was <hi>Iohn Baptist. Nero</hi> also, that bloody persecutour of Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, is said to haue had such a guiltie Conscience, that he thought that all the Christians which hee had put to death, followed him: and at last, when he had slaine his deare friend <hi>Symmachus,</hi> his accusing Conscience did so torment him, that sitting at meat, he thought the eyes of <hi>Symmachus</hi> looked on him in euery Dish; and so fell vpon his owne Sword, and killed himselfe. Thus you see how God will haue account of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent blood-shed, and wil be auenged on them that shed it.</p>
            <p>And sixtly, vnlesse such bloody wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches doe repent truely while this time of grace lastes, they shall goe vnder Gods heauy wrath for euer. Our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Christ saith, <hi>Whosoeuer killeth, shall be</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5. 21.</note>
               <hi>culpable of iudgement.</hi> The Apostle <hi>Paul</hi> pronounceth of them. <hi>That they shall not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 21.</note>
               <hi>inherite the Kingdome of heauen. They shall</hi>
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:20306:61"/>
               <hi>haue their part in the Lake that burneth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 5. 21.</note>
               <hi>with Fire and Brimstone. And they shall be shut out of Gods Kingdome, with Dogges,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 21. 8.</note>
               <hi>Enchanters, Whoremongers, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 22. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Lastly, this sinne is aggrauated by consideration of the person Killed, or Murthered.</p>
            <p>If it be a great sinne to Kill any Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian; much more a Saint, or Child of God, who is deare to him; in whom God delighteth, and in whom the image of God doth chiefly shine; and in whom Christ Iesus is persecuted: <note place="margin">Act. 9. 4.</note> because who so killeth such a one, doth (as it were) sheath his Sword in the heart of Christ. <hi>For wee are members of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe. 5. 30.</note>
               <hi>his body, of his flesh, and of his bones.</hi> If hee which killed <hi>Kain,</hi> a wicked man, <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 15.</note> should be punished seauen fould, What is to be said of him, who killeth a godly man? Yea, What of those that haue killed the Saints, and Martirs of Iesus Christ? It is vnpossible but that their blood should cry aloud for vengeance. <hi>How long Lord, holy, and true; dost thou not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 6. 9. 10.</note>
               <hi>iudge and auenge our blood on them that dwell on the Earth.</hi> Let the Strumpet of <hi>Rome</hi> looke to this, <hi>Who hath been many</hi>
               <pb n="115" facs="tcp:20306:61"/>
               <hi>yeeres drunken with the blood of the Saintes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 17. 6.</note>
               <hi>and with the blood of the Martyrs of Iesus.</hi> In the tenne Persecutions, it was coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted good sport in the Romaine Empire to kill, and murther Christians in great multitudes, when they were gathered togeather in Prayers. In that bloody <hi>Nero</hi> his time, they vsed to make Bone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiers with the bones of Christians, whom they had Murthered: In which bloody Persecution, the poore Church, and Children of God, remayned from the Ascention of Christ, almost the space of foure Hundred yeares, till that blessed Emperour <hi>Constantine</hi> the great, sonne of <hi>Helena</hi> an English woman, established the Church of Christ: At which time, that good Bishop <hi>Eusebius,</hi> writer of the Ecclesiasticall Historie, obtained Licence, and Letters of autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, vnder the hand &amp; seale of the said Emperour, to make search throughout all the Monarchie of <hi>Rome,</hi> of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of all those that had suffered in that time of Persecution, for the Fayth and testimonie of Iesus Christ; and it was found (as <hi>Hierom</hi> writing to <hi>Chromatius</hi> and <hi>Heliodorus,</hi> doth witnesse) that there
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:20306:62"/> had been put to death in that time, for euery day in the Kalender, fiue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Martirs, except onely the first of Ianuarie; which day was festiually kept throughout their <hi>Romaine</hi> Empire, for the choosing of their Consuls.</p>
            <p>What need I speake of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the blood of the blessed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirs, which was shed in this land, by that drunken Whore of <hi>Rome,</hi> while that Church vsurped supremacie in this Realme, during the reigne of Queene <hi>Mary:</hi> and yet doth that vnsatiable monster still thirst after more blood.</p>
            <p>To end this part, let al Gods children take heed of Killing with heart, tongue, or hand: Let the life of man be preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <note place="margin">1. Sam 26. 21. Pro. 24. 11.</note> in our eyes. And be it farre from vs, that wee should defile our hands with the blood of any of Gods children, least so we should be guiltie of this sinne, as were the people of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <note place="margin">Mat 23. 37.</note> the Prophets, &amp; stoned them which were sent to them, and with whom the Lord hath a controuersie for this, and other their sinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(And Stealing)</hi> All manner of vniust <note place="margin">Stealing.</note> coueting, getting, or with-holding of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:20306:62"/> that (which by the right of proprietie) is not a mans owne, is theft. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet doth not heere meane onely such poore and pettie Theeues, as are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly arraigned at euery Sessions, but such as steale by Oppression, Extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Vsurie, and the like. There be few that can truly say with <hi>Samuel, Behold heere I am, beare record of mee, before the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 12. 3. 4.</note>
               <hi>Lord, and before his Annoynted; Whose Oxe haue I taken? or whose Asse haue I taken? or whom haue I done wrong to? or whom haue I hurt, or of whom haue I receiued any bribe, to blind mine eyes therewith, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, such Captaines as hauing the conduct or leading of Souldiers, purse vp the Princes pay to their owne vse, or else prodigally spend it, and so pinch the poore Souldiers, and pine them, that they are glad to leape at a crust, and often brought so low and weake, that they are forced to vse vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull meanes to get food, and shortly become vnfit for any seruice.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, such as beeing in Office in the Common-wealth, doe more respect Bribes, and their owne priuate gaine, then either Law or Conscience: and if
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:20306:63"/> vnhappily they buy their Offices, then is all Fish that commeth to Nette with them, catch that catch may: then must the poore Countrey people pay for that.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, they that get the Goods of Orphants, or poore fatherlesse Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren into their handes, and either de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraude them of the most part of it; or else driue them to Law, and so cause them to spende as much sometimes, as their Portions come too, before they can recouer that their Parentes left them.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, Tradesmen also sometimes, play the Theeues, and sinne againg the Law of God, by oppressing those that deale with them, in so much as <hi>Caueat</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 25. 14</note>
               <hi>emptor,</hi> Let the buyer take heed, is fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in euery mans mouth: But God saith not so, for Christian charitie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth that the seller looke vnto it, that hee bee not both a Chapman and a Theefe, but that he sell a penny-worth for a Penny, and vse a good Conscience <note place="margin">Amos. 8. 6.</note> in his Trade: not to sell counterfaite Wares for good; not to vse false <note place="margin">Deut. 25. 13. 14.</note> Waights or Measures, nor to buy by
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:20306:63"/> one Waight or Measure, and sell by an <note place="margin">Leuit. 19. 36 Pro. 11. 2</note> other: which God forbiddeth, and is abhominable to the Lord.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, and lastly, (for I will make mention of no more) are all such as beare a gallant shew in the World, and gather other mens Goods into their hands, and when they haue runne as farre as their credite will reach, then turne Banck-rupts vpon the sodaine, bearing the world in hand, that they are not worth a Groate, when as they keepe a great masse of other mens Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney secretly to themselues, so that their Creditours are glad to grow to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position, and take that little they can quietly come by: But when euery mans mouth is stopt with a thing of naught, then they shift themselues into some corner of the Country where they are not knowen, and there ruffle it out with other mens Riches, liue in all brauerie, put that foorth to Vsurie, which they haue stolne from others; and so become double and damnable theeues to the Common-wealth: whose Iudgement I leaue to the Lord.</p>
            <p>Let vs make vse of this, to our selues;
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:20306:64"/> And let euery one of vs that loue the God of Truth, hate all false-getting of the Goods of this world, and labour in our seuerall places and callings to carry a good conscience, to rest satisfied with <hi>meum</hi> and <hi>tuum,</hi> not to desire, purloyne, or with-hold that, which in right is none of our owne: And if any of vs haue fallen this way, let vs with <hi>Zacheus</hi> make restitution, as Gods law com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth; <note place="margin">Luk. 19. 8. Exod. 22. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. Nehe. 5. 11, 12, 13. Psal. 67. 1.</note> so shall Gods wrath be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pezed, the controuersie ended, and <hi>God will blesse vs, shew vs the light of his countenance, and be mercifull vnto vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>(And Whoring.)</hi> Whoredome is a fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and abhominable, but yet a vulgar <note place="margin">Whoring.</note> sinne, a number of sinnes attend vpon <note place="margin">Math. 5. 28.</note> it. It is taken for all vncleannesse of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and minde. I will onely speake of it in act; which hath particular degrees. When it is committed betweene a man and woman both vnmarried, it is called Fornication: If both, or the one party be married, it is called Adulterie: If the parties bee within the Degrees forbid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>den, <note place="margin">Leuit. 18.</note> it is Incest: If forcibly committed it is a Rape. And though one of these be more horrible sinne then another,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:20306:64"/> yet <hi>The wages of the least is death.</hi> And therefore S. <hi>Augustine</hi> saith, <hi>Omnia peccata</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 23.</note>
               <hi>sunt mortalia, sed omnia peccata non sunt equalia:</hi> which may serue to condemne the errour of the Papistes, who hold, that some sinnes in their owne nature are Veniall, and some are Mortall: But the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> saith, <hi>That the same</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 18. 20.</note>
               <hi>Soule that sinneth, shall die.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> telles them, that if it bee a sinne, (mince it as they may) <hi>The wages of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 23.</note>
               <hi>it is death,</hi> without repentance and Gods mercie. And the same Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> would haue them know, <hi>That if the Wicked will returne from all his sinnes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 18. 21. 27.</note>
               <hi>that hee hath committed, and doe that which is lawfull and right, hee shall saue his Soule aliue.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the least sinne without repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Gods mercy, is damnable: and the greatest sinne, if it be truely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of, and Gods mercy in Christ apprehended by a liuely Fayth, while wee beleeue in this time of Grace, it is pardonable.</p>
            <p>This sinne of Whoredome is a filthy and abhominable sinne, hated of God, and all good men, and that for many
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:20306:65"/> reasons.</p>
            <p>First, because it taketh away the Heart of a man, as sayth this our Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Whoredome, Wine, and new Wine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hose. 4, 11.</note>
               <hi>take away the Heart.</hi> As <hi>Nebuchadnezer</hi> had the Heart of a Beast; so when a Whoremonger is that way giuen, hee is carryed headlong with his beastly affections. The Heart is the principall <note place="margin">Pro. 23. 26.</note> part of man in Gods seruice. And our Sauiour Christ sayth, <hi>Thou shalt loue the Lord thy God with all thy Heart.</hi> And the <note place="margin">Mat. 22. 32.</note> Apostle would haue vs serue God hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily. If the Heart be away, no seruice <note place="margin">Col. 3. 24.</note> can be acceptable to God: But Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome taketh away the Heart, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Whoremongers can performe no seruice acceptable to God. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soeuer the Body of the Whoremai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ster is, his Heart is with his Whore; and where euer the Whore bee, her Heart is with her Whoremonger. The Whoremonger is so besotted, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitute <note place="margin">Pro. 6. 32.</note> of vnderstanding, <hi>That hee goeth about his businesse like a Foole to the Stockes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro 7. 22.</note> It made <hi>Dauid</hi> such a Foole for the time, that hee went about to couer his sinne, by murthering of his trusty Seruant
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:20306:65"/>
               <hi>Ʋrias.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, because it is a brutish sin, it maketh a man a beast, though a man in shape, yet a beast in behauiour. <note place="margin">Math. 7. 6. Luk. 13. 32. Iere. 5. 8. Prou. 7. 22. Deut. 23. 18. Reu. 21. 8.</note> Whoremongers are cōpared to beasts: to fed horses: To an Oxe led to the slaughter. The price of an whore and a dogge is all one. By a dogge he mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth as an impudent wretch. Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers are as dogges, and whores as bitches; nay, worse then beastes are they.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, because it hath a lawfull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. <hi>To auoyd fornication</hi> (saith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle) <hi>let euery man haue his wife, and let euery woman haue her owne husband. They</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 2, 9.</note>
               <hi>that cannot abstaine, let them marry: where there is a lawfull remedy, the sinne is more grieuous.</hi> God gaue to <hi>Adam</hi> the fruite of <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 16.</note> all the trees in Paradise, but one: hee would not be satisfied with that, but he would needes eate of the fruite of that one tree also which was forbidden, therefore his sinne was the greater. A poore theefe is pittied that stealeth to <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 33.</note> satisfie his hunger; but he that stealeth and hath enough of his owne, his sinne is the greater, and more to be punished.
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:20306:66"/> So he that hath a lawfull remedy, and such a remedy as God hath ordained for mans good and comfort, and not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding runneth a whoring, his sin is the more abhominable, and deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth greater punishment. Such was <hi>Dauids</hi> sinne, he had many wiues and concubines, and therefore well proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that way, yet hee tooke another <note place="margin">2. Sam. 12. 4 6, 7, 8, 9, 13.</note> mans wife, and therefore his sinne (by his owne confession) was more hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, because Sathan thereby gaineth two soules at once, a theese may steale alone, the drunkard may be drunken alone, the murtherer, swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer, &amp;c. may sinne alone: But the whoremonger killeth two soules at a clap: nay, sometimes Satan gaineth many soules by meanes of one whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger or one strumpet. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Ambrose</hi> vpon that, <hi>Can a man take fire in his bosome, and his cloathes not bee</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 27. 28.</note>
               <hi>burnt? Or can a man goe vpon coales, and his feet not bee burnt?</hi> And (sayth that Father) how can a strumpet dwell in a towne, and young men not be drawne to whoredome? If the blood of <hi>Habel</hi>
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:20306:66"/> cryed for vengeance, how much more shall those soules cry for vengeance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the whore-monger which are lost through his default? The whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger careth not how many he abuse, nay, the more, the more he reioyceth: and the strumpet careth not how many she leades to the Deuill, the more custo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers the more merryer, and the more money too, <hi>shee openeth her quiuer against</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccelesias<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus 26, 12.</note>
               <hi>euery arrow.</hi> But if they knew that all those soules would crie, and pleade vengeance against them, who haue sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by their meanes, they would turne a new leafe, and returne to the Lord, while time of grace lasteth.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, because whoremongers are the Deuils factors, Satan is a tempter, <note place="margin">Math. 4. 13.</note> so are they. Honest women may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere them as Christ did <hi>Peter,</hi> when he went about to intice him to saue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, <hi>Get thee behind mee Satan, thou art</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16, 23.</note>
               <hi>an offence vnto mee:</hi> So may they answere those members of Satan, that tempt them to whoredome. And as when the Diuell shewed Christ <hi>all the Kingdomes of the world, and the glory of them, and sayd</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 4. 8▪ 9. 10.</note>
               <hi>vnto him, All these will I giue thee, if thou</hi>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:20306:67"/>
               <hi>wilt fall downe and worship mee:</hi> but Iesus answered, auoid Satan. So when whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers doe offer vnto women, gold, siluer, riches, or great preferments, as the price of their honesty, and soules too, if they wil fall downe to their filthy lust, they may answere the members as Iesus Christ did the head, Auoid Satan, thou tempting Deuill, get thee hence. Whosoeuer laboureth to draw others <note place="margin">Act. 13. 8. 10.</note> from God, he is Satans Factor, a child of the Deuill, and an enemie to righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ousnesse. When thou hearest or seest such, thou hearest or seest a right mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Satan, let all Gods children take heed of them.</p>
            <p>Sixtly, because the whoremonger sinneth against the honour of his owne body, and that many wayes. First, <hi>the bodies of Christians are the temples of the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 19. 1. Iohn 2. 17.</note>
               <hi>holy Ghost,</hi> and the holy Ghost is that oyntment. As wee will not put sweet oyntment into a stincking boxe: so God will not haue his spirit dwell in a stincking body polluted with whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. It banisheth the holy spirit of God, and maketh the body a den for deuils. It is a great offence to plucke
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:20306:67"/> downe the Pallace of a Prince, but a greater to defile the temple of God, for <hi>If any man destroy the temple of God, him will God destroy, for the temple of God is ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 17.</note>
               <hi>which wee are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, because our bodies are the members of Christ, but the whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger cuts himselfe off from being a member of Christ, and maketh himselfe a member of an harlot. <hi>Shall I take the</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 15.</note>
               <hi>members of Christ</hi> (sayth <hi>Paul) and make them the members of an harlot? God forbid.</hi> Wee are vnited to Christ, yea, wee are married to Christ, he is our husband, we are his spouse, we are one with him. <note place="margin">Ephe. 5. 30.</note> How fearefull a thing is it then for a man to rend and dismember himselfe from the body of Christ, and make himselfe a member of an harlot?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, he sinneth against his owne <note place="margin">Prou. 5. 11. Prou. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. Num. 5. 22. 27.</note> body, because he consumeth and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steth his body. Rotten diseases belong to this sinne. The French pocks, and fearefull diseases accompany it, yea, <note place="margin">Ecclus 19. 3.</note> rottennesse and wormes shal haue them to heritage.</p>
            <p>Seauenthly, because as the whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>master sinneth against his owne body,
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:20306:68"/> so also against his owne outward state and goods, for whoredome is the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way to pouerty. <hi>Hee that feedeth harlots</hi> (saith <hi>Salomon) wasteth his substance.</hi> The <note place="margin">Prou. 29. 3.</note> prodigall sonne hauing spent vp all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong harlots and bad women, was in the end brought to such want, that he was glad to play the Swine-heard, and to <hi>eate huskes among the Swyne.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <note place="margin">Luk. 5. 13. 16. 20.</note>
               <hi>Salomon</hi> againe sayth, <hi>Because of the whorish woman, a man is brought to a mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell of bread, and a woman will hunt for the precious life of a man.</hi> Whores are the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 26.</note> branches to hunt a mans soule to a morsell of bread. Whoredome is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to fire, because it will wast, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume, and destroy. <hi>Whoredome is a fire</hi> (sayth <hi>Iob) that shall deuoure to destruction, and which will eate out all a mans increase.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob 31. 12.</note> Nay, it is worse then fire: fire consu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth but earthly things, but the fire of whoredome will consume and burne both soule and body, vnlesse it be quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with teares of repentance. And therfore the Lord hauing charged them with Adulterie, sayth, <hi>Hee will melt them</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere▪ 9. 2, 7.</note>
               <hi>to destruction.</hi> When a man or woman is giuen vp to whoredome, then the diuell
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:20306:68"/> runnes away with all, whores haue one part, bawdes another, and the secret curse of God consumeth the rest. Giue an harlot as much as thou wilt, and fee her, and feede her while she will aske, and she shall be neuer the richer, but thou shalt be the poorer; and what though it prosper for a while with some whores, yet in the end the least blast of Gods vengeance will blow all away.</p>
            <p>Eightly, because the whoremonger and whore sinne against their own cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite, estimation, and good name: for <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 33.</note> this sinne robbes a man of his good re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, and brands him with a note of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famy. <note place="margin">Ecclus. 19. 2. Prou. 5. 9.</note>
               <hi>Their reproach shall neuer be put out.</hi> A mans honour, which is his credite, and honesty, is so lost.</p>
            <p>Ninthly, because it brings an accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing conscience, if thou knewest but the tenth part of the horrour that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> endured and suffered for his Adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terie, thou wouldest not for a thousand worlds commit Adulterie.</p>
            <p>Tenthly, because Gods institution concerning Matrimony is so polluted, the couenant betweene God and man made in Baptisme is broken, and so is
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:20306:69"/> the couenant betweene man and wife. They are theeues to God, because by whoredom they steale away from God their soules and bodies, which are not their own but Gods, for Christ bought them with a deere price. The husband <note place="margin">1. Cor. 6. 19. 20.</note> steales from his wife that body which is none of his owne, but his wiues, and the adultresse stealeth from her husband that body which is not her owne, but <note place="margin">1. Cor. 7. 3. 4.</note> her husbands. And further, the whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monger doth not onely dishoner her body with whom he commits the sin, but also he is a theefe to her husband, in robbing him of his owne flesh, and pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling (as it were) the heart out of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, in taking her, whom he makes as much account of as his owne heart.</p>
            <p>Besides all this, it is an abhominable sinne, because God forbids it, and all the <note place="margin">Exo. 20. 14. Ephes. 5. 3. Gen. 39. 12.</note> godly abhorre it. <hi>Ioseph</hi> chose rather to indanger his life, then to consent to the lust of his filthie mistris. <hi>Susanna,</hi> rather then she would yeeld to the elders, and <note place="margin">Dan. 13. 45.</note> lose her honestie, aduentured her body to the fire, and burned she had beene, had not God deliuered her. But in this sinfull age, many will aduenture their
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:20306:69"/> liues to doe it, and so farre are some from <hi>Iosephs</hi> affection, in fleeing from bad women, that they hunt after them, till they cast themselues headlong into destruction. Yea, the very Heathens <note place="margin">Rom. 2, 14, 15. Gen. 12. 18. 19. Gen. 20. 25. 9.</note> which knew not God, but were led by the light of nature, did hate and abhorre adulterie, as may be seene in <hi>Pharao,</hi> and <hi>Abimelech.</hi> When <hi>Dionisius</hi> the King vnderstood that the young Prince, his sonne, had layen with a mans wife, hee sharpely reprooued him, and asked him, if euer he knew, or heard of any such filthinesse committed by him? The Prince answered no: your father was not a King. No more (saith <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisius)</hi> shall thy sonne be King, vnlesse thou amend thy manners. It is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, a famous conquerour, but an heathen man, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ouercome <hi>Darius</hi> King of <hi>Persia,</hi> could in no wise bee perswaded to see the Queene, <hi>Darius</hi> his wife, who was reported to be wonderfull faire, least he might haue beene tempted to lust after her. Shall not these heathen men, which knew not God, rise vp in iudgement against many Christians, which are so
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:20306:70"/> farre from vsing meanes to auoid this sin, that they follow it with greedines, and vse all meanes to stirre themselues vp to lust.</p>
            <p>Lastly, God will not onely afflict temporall punishments vpon whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers <note place="margin">Num. 25. 9. Iere. 5. 7. 8. 9. 2. Sam. 12. 10. Ecclus. 19. 3 Prou. 31. 3. Prou. 6. 32. Mal. 3. 5. 1. Cor. 3. 17. 1. Cor. 6. 9, 10. Hebr. 13 4. Reu. 21. 8. &amp; 22, 15.</note> in this life, but also (vnlesse they repent) there shalbe no place for them in heauen. <hi>The adulterer</hi> (saith <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon) destroyeth his owne soule. The Lord will come neere to them in Iudgement, and will be a swift witnesse against them,</hi> (saith the Prophet <hi>Malachi.) God will destroy them,</hi> saith <hi>Paul, they shall not inherit the kingdome of heauen. God will iudge them. They shall haue their portion in the lake that burneth with fire and brimstone, and shall be shut out of Gods kingdome with dogges, mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See then what an abhominable sinne this is, and what whoremongers gaine by their whoredom. <hi>The fairest end of it is shame and repentance,</hi> as in <hi>Dauid, Magda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 21.</note> and others, which thing the very Heathens well considered, for <hi>Demost<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henes</hi> the Philosopher (as <hi>Aulus Gel.</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordeth <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Aul. Gel. noct. Att. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ca,</hi> 8.</note> out of <hi>Phocion)</hi> hearing of the fame, or rather infamy, of that notable
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:20306:70"/> strumpet <hi>Lais</hi> of <hi>Corinth,</hi> hee went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther secretly, thinking to haue the vse of her body: shee asked him no lesse for a nights worke then tenne thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Tallents, which is valued to be worth of our coyne a thousand french Crownes. The Philosopher answered her, <hi>Non emo tanti poenitere,</hi> I buy not repentance so deare. Let euery one la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to keepe his vessell in holynesse and honour; and let them which haue fallen this way be ashamed of their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <note place="margin">1. Thes. 4. 4. Psal. 78. 18.</note> and filthie former life, and fall to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance while they haue time, least the Heathens at the day of Iudgement cry vengeance against them. And let euery one of vs be carefull to auoid all occasions that may stirre vs vp to this sinne; and let vs not abuse Gods crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to lust; Let vs make a couenant with our eyes, as <hi>Iob</hi> did; and let vs <note place="margin">Pro. 7. 15 16. Pro. 23. 31. 33. Rom. 13 13. Iob 31. 1. Pro. 1. 6. 23. 24. Prou. 7. 5. Prou. 2. 16.</note> meditate vpon the word of God, which is a forcible meane against this sinne; it shall keepe vs from the bad woman, <hi>which flattereth with her lips, forsaketh the husband of her youth, and breaketh the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of her God.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="134" facs="tcp:20306:71"/>
            <q>By swearing, and lying, and killing, and stealing, and whoring, they breake out, and bloud toucheth bloud.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>(They breake out.)</hi> The Prophet am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifieth their sinnes by a metaphor of breaking out, alluding to a streame of water, which hauing gotten a little is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sue, soone becommeth a great flood, and rusheth out with violence.</p>
            <p>When men breake out and runne headlong into sinne, commonly they grow impudent and shamelesse in their sinnes, then they sinne before God, <note place="margin">Gen. 6. 11.</note> they grow to such impudency, that they care not though God and man see them; <hi>Then they carrie their sinnes in their foreheads, they haue whores faces, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 3. 3.</note>
               <hi>will not be ashamed: Yea, the tryall of their countenance testifieth against them: they declare their sinnes as</hi> Sodom, <hi>and hide</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay 3. 9.</note>
               <hi>them not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a miserable thing to see bad men breake out, and runne headlong into sinne without shame, as if an impudent strumpet should play the harlot in her husbands sight; and yet men now adaies are growen so shamelesse in sinne, that
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:20306:71"/> (for the most part) they froath out their owne shame, and brag and boast of their bad deeds. Who is ashamed of pride, whoredome, drunckennesse? &amp;c. Doe not blasphemous swearers, extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners, vsurers, &amp;c. seeke to outface sinne, and neuer blush at it? Many are more ashamed to doe good then euill, and some are more abashed at their base apparell, then their bad liues: yea, though God afflict vs from yeare to yeare with new iudgements, yet still wee rush headlong into sinne, without shame? What yeare of late hath escaped vs, wherein God hath not threatned vs with pestilence, dearth, or vnseasonable weather, and yet still wee breake out into sinne. Let vs then breake off our course of sinne betime, least Gods iudgements breake out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst vs, and his decree passe out vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs.</p>
            <p>Againe, whereas this people did breake out into sinne, as men impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and shamelesse in their sinnes, it sheweth, that they were farre from true repentance, for where shame of sinne is wanting, there can be no true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:20306:72"/> The Lord therefore complained that the Iewes were not ashamed, <hi>when they had committed abhomination. What</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 8. 12.</note>
               <hi>profit</hi> (sayth the Apostle to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manes) <hi>had ye of those things whereof you</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 21.</note>
               <hi>are now ashamed?</hi> While <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Heuah</hi> were in the state of innocency, though they were naked, yet were they not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed, but sinne brought shame, and therefore they hid themselues, and sow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <note place="margin">Gen. 3. 7.</note> fig-tree leaues together, and made themselues breeches. <hi>Magdalen</hi> was so ashamed after she saw the filthinesse of her sinne, and what she had deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, that cōming into the house where Christ was, she stood at his feet behind him, weeping, and began to <hi>wash his feet with teares, and wiped them with the haires of her head;</hi> all which shewed a shame <note place="margin">Luk. 7. 38.</note> and loathing of her sinne. The Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall child after he came to true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of his bad course of life <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> to his father, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>called his sonne.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 15. 21.</note> And the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> was so a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shamed <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>a farre off, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk 18. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>They <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> ashamed of
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:20306:72"/> their sinnes, are farre from repentance, but shame will bee a good meane to bring men to repentance; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apostle requireth the Thessa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians <note place="margin">2. Thes. 3. 14. 1. Cor. 5. 9, 10, 11. Math, 18. 17.</note> to excommunicate the obsti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, <hi>and haue no company with them, that they may be ashamed.</hi> Yea, saith Christ, <hi>let him be to thee as a heathen man, and a Publicane,</hi> which may serue to reprooue those who haue familiarity with blas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemous swearers, cōmon drunkards, knowen Adulterers, obstinate Papists, or excommunicated persons; such fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Satans worke, and hearten bad men in their sinnes, whereas if men would auoid their company, they would grow ashamed of themselues, and be brought to repentance.</p>
            <p>Further, where the Prophet sayth, <hi>That they breake out into sinne.</hi> It appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth that they were not onely impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, but also hardned in their sinnes. Of this hardnesse of heart the Apostle warneth the Hebrewes; <hi>Take heed, least</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3. 12.</note>
               <hi>there be in any of you an euill heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is a fearefull thing to be brought to hardnesse of heart. <hi>Hee that hardeneth his heart</hi> (sayth <hi>Salomon) shall fall into</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 28. 14.</note>
               <pb n="138" facs="tcp:20306:73"/>
               <hi>euill.</hi> So <hi>Zedekia</hi> hardened his necke, <hi>and made his heart obstinate, that hee might not returne to the Lord God of Israel.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Chro. 36. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>He that breaketh out into sinne with an hardned heart, seeth not in what a desperate state hee stands. As when a sick man feeleth not that he is sicke, or a man wounded to death, will not bee perswaded that he is hurt: so desperate is hee and vncureable, that breakes out into sinne with an hardned heart, and hath no feeling of his sinne: for when the heart is once growne hard, then the working of Gods spirit is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away.</p>
            <p>Againe, his state is desperate, that breakes out into sinne with an hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned heart, because nothing can stay him: As it is an hard thing to stop a violent streame of water, forcibly brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out; so difficult a thing is it, to stay him that with an hardned heart rusheth out headlong into sinne. When <hi>Dauids</hi> heart was hardned a while in sinne, and himselfe brake out into a bad course of life, (though God crossed him many <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11.</note> waies to haue stayed him) yet on hee goes, nothing would worke vppon
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:20306:73"/> him, till he had added murther to his adulterie, and so blood touched blood. When <hi>Balaam</hi> had once taken a bad way, nothing could hinder him (though <note place="margin">Num. 22.</note> God vsed wonderfull meanes) still for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward goeth he with his wickednes. And when <hi>Iudas</hi> his heart was hardned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst <note place="margin">Mat. 26. 48. Mar. 14. 11.</note> Christ, there was no stay with him, he waked when others slept, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause he would effect his intented trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son. It is much adoe (saith one) to stay him that rideth on the Deuill; so head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long runne they that breake out into sinne with hardned hearts.</p>
            <p>Let euery one take heed how hee thus breakes out into sinne: the ground that is hard, will not suffer the purest seed to grow in it; neither will an hard heart suffer the celestiall seede of the word to take roote in it, nor the spirit of God to worke vpon it. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when thou commest to heare the word of God, <hi>which is the power of God to saluation to euery one that beleeueth,</hi> bring <note place="margin">Rom. 1. 16.</note> with thee a melting heart, for if thine heart be hardned, the word (which is the ordinary meanes of thy conuersion and saluation) will not worke vpon
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:20306:74"/> thee, nay, thou hearest it to thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation. And when thou feelest any heate, or sparke of Gods spirit, then presently blow at it, and vse all good meanes, that thine adamant heart may be pearced with the word, and opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the spirit.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(They breake out)</hi> Lastly, where the Prophet chargeth this people that they breake out by swearing, lying, killing, stealing, whoring, &amp;c. I doe further note, that there are degrees in sinne, and when a man is once entred into a bad course, hee euer breakes out to <note place="margin">Iere. 9. 3.</note> worse and worse, vnlesse God stay him. As a spring sends out but a small streame at first, but the further it run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the more small brookes ioyne with it, till it become a great Riuer: So the longer a bad man runneth on in sinne, the more sinnes he heapes vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> sayth, <hi>The beginning of strife is as one that openeth the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 17 14. Ecclus 3. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Psal. 1. 1.</note>
               <hi>waters, &amp;c. Dauid</hi> makes mention of three steps of sinne, walking, standing, and sitting downe in sinne. When a man is resolued to sit him downe, and rest in sinne, then he maketh but a iest
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:20306:74"/> of Gods threats. The wicked and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theists count three sorts of people hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, <hi>The proud</hi> (say they) <hi>are blessed, they that worke wickednesse, are set vp, and they</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mal. 3. 15.</note>
               <hi>that tempt God, yea, they are deliuered.</hi> See how <hi>Kain</hi> brake out into sinne, and blood touched blood.</p>
            <p>First, <hi>Hee was angrie at his brothers sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, then hee hated him, then hee killed him,</hi> then hee was so blockish, that hee thought God sawe not his sinne, and <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 5, 8.</note> therefore made a lye to God, and lastly, he despaired of Gods mercie. Sinne will grow to a streame, if it be not resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted in time. <hi>The floods of wickednesse</hi> (sayd <hi>Dauid) made mee afrayd.</hi> Sinne is like <note place="margin">Psal. 18. 4.</note> the spaune of a Fish, it will increase to a multitude. <hi>As one deepe calleth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 42. 9.</note> so one sinne brings on ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: and as one disease of the body (if it be not in time cured) brings in a many moe, so doth one disease of the soule: and as hee that hath the drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sie, when he hath drunke is the dryer; so when a man hath entred into a bad course of life, for the most part, hee breakes out with more violence, into sinne.</p>
            <pb n="142" facs="tcp:20306:75"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> was a man beloued of God, hee rose euery night at mid-night to <note place="margin">Psal. 119. 62. Psal. 55. 18.</note> praier, but how did he breake out from one sinne to other, because he did not resist the first motions of sinne? First he saw <hi>Bethsheba</hi> washing her selfe, then hee lusted after her, then hee lay with <note place="margin">2. Sam. 11. 2. 4.</note> her, then hee vsed many bad and sinfull meanes whereby to hide his sinne; and lastly, hee caused <hi>Ʋrias</hi> to be slaine.</p>
            <p>The like wee see in <hi>Peter</hi> a notable Apostle of Christ Iesus, ready to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swere at euery turne; First, at the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund <note place="margin">Math. 26. 70. 72. 74.</note> of the silly wench hee denyed his Master Christ; then hee sware hee knew him not; and lastly, hee cursed himselfe, and sware, he knew not the man.</p>
            <p>If God had giuen <hi>Kain</hi> grace to haue resisted sinne at first, he had not growen to that extremity of sinne.</p>
            <p>If <hi>Dauid</hi> had withstood Sathans temptations, when hee saw <hi>Bethsheba</hi> washing her, he had neuer broken out to that height of sinne, as he did.</p>
            <p>And if <hi>Peter</hi> had stopt sinne at first when it brake out by simple denyall, he had neuer runne headlong to swea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:20306:75"/> and cursing.</p>
            <p>If such excellent men as <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> went so farre, because they resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sted not sinne at first, let all Gods chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren take heed of Sathans subtilty, and withstand the first motions of sinne, and cut it downe while it is sprouting; for if sinne and Satan get the least enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment, they will till thee on from bad to worse, till there bee no remedy: <note place="margin">Mat. 12. 45.</note> and as one deuill brought in seauen, so one sinne will bring in many.</p>
            <p>As he that runneth downe a hill can hardly stay himselfe till he come to the bottome; so hee that beginneth a bad course of life, can hardly stay his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions till hee come to the extreamity of sinne.</p>
            <p>It is a fearefull thing to goe on from sinne to sinne, so as bloud touch bloud, and one sinne follow in the neck of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and therefore wee should <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>staine from all appearance of euill.</hi> And as <note place="margin">1. Thes. 5. 22.</note> wee are carefull not onely to auoyd the pestilence, but also not to come neere the clothes that are infected with it; so let vs not onely labour to smo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wicked motions at first, but also
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:20306:76"/>
               <hi>euen hate the very garment spotted with the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg, 23.</note>
               <hi>flesh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> and <hi>Peter</hi> being admonished, straight wayes repented: so let vs de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy sinne while it is young, least if it take head, it destroy vs.</p>
            <p>And as he was blessed that tooke the children of the Babilonians, <hi>and dashed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 137. 9.</note>
               <hi>them against the stones,</hi> so shalt thou be blessed, if thou takest thy sinnes while they are yong, and killest them, as it were in the cradle, and destroyest them. But woe to thee, if thou suffer thy sinnes to domineere, to growe to an head, and to breake out, like a violent streame, till one blood-giltines touch another, and then is thy state more dangerous, because greeuous sinnes must haue great repentance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(And blood toucheth blood.)</hi> Blood is <note place="margin">Esay 1. 15. Deut. 17. 8.</note> not onely taken in the Scriptures for murther, but also for great and grosse sinnes. In all ages of the world sinne hath abounded, I need not to set down particulers thereof, let all the bookes of the Bible testifie the trueth of this proposition. And let vs looke to our selues, in this yron age of the world,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:20306:76"/> and see if all sorts of people doe not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so now breake out into sinne? Hath not all flesh now corrupted his way vpon earth, as in <hi>Noah</hi> his time? Is it not with vs, as in <hi>Dauids</hi> time? Do <hi>not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 12. 2.</note>
               <hi>most men flatter with their lippes, and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>semble in their double hearts.</hi> May we not truely say, <hi>That deceipt and guile goe not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 55, 11.</note>
               <hi>out of our streetes.</hi> Are not <hi>Ioabs</hi> daggers, and <hi>Iudas</hi> his kisses commonly put in practise among vs? and therefore let vs consider how the Prophet in the next verse, denounceth Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments against them, and tells them, that the land shall mourne.</p>
            <p>
               <q>Therefore shall the Land mourne, and <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Verse</hi> 3.</note> euery one that dwelleth therein shall bee cut off, with the beastes of the field, and with the foules of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and also the fishes of the Sea shall be taken away.</q>
            </p>
            <p>THis verse containeth the fourth part of my former diuision, namely, the temporall iudgements of God against this people for their sinnes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>(Therefore</hi> (saith he) <hi>shall the Land</hi>
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:20306:77"/>
               <hi>mourne, &amp;c.</hi> As the land is sayd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce, when God blessed it with plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; <note place="margin">Esay 30. 23. Ioel 2. 21. Psal. 65. 14.</note> and the vallies are sayd to laugh and sing, when they stand thick with corne, so heere it is sayd, The Land shall mourne, when God shall curse it with barrennesse, for mans sinne; and so also the Prophet <hi>Esay</hi> sayth, <hi>The earth lamenteth, and fadeth away. A fruitefull</hi>
               <note place="margin">Esay 22. 4.</note>
               <hi>Land</hi> (saith <hi>Dauid) hee maketh barren for</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 12. 4. Lam. 1. 4. Psal. 107. 34.</note>
               <hi>the wickednesse of them that dwell therein.</hi> If the earth were Gold (as one sayth) the grasse Pearles, the trees Siluer, and the fields full of corne and cattell, yet will not God spare any of them for mans sinne. The earth hath comely Closes, fruitefull Fieldes, Vineyards, <note place="margin">Zeph. 1. 13. 17.</note> Orchards, Gardens, Cities, Towers, Townes, and stately buildings, God will destroy them, and make them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solate for mans sinne.</p>
            <p>Not onely is man punished for sinne, but also the Lande, and other vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable and vnsensible creatures: the Land carrieth the curse of bryers, <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 12. Gen. 6. 13.</note> thornes, and thistles, for mans sinne. And as sinne increaseth, so Gods curse vppon the earth, and all that is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:20306:77"/> likewise increaseth.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Noah</hi> his time, for mans sinne, the Land mourned, and all that dwelt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were cut off (except onely eight persons) with the beastes of the field, foules of the aire, and liuing things on the earth were destroyed, nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serued, but what was in the Arke. In <hi>Pharao</hi> his time, <hi>the waters were turned</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 7. 4.</note>
               <hi>into blood;</hi> the earth was poysoned with Frogges, infected with Flies, the Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell <note place="margin">Exod. 7. 19. 20. Exod. 8. 6. 14. 21. Exod. 9. 3. 19. 21.</note> dyed with murraine, the trees, and hearbs are smitten with haile, their bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and flaxe that should feed and cloath them, were destroyed for their sinnes.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Saul</hi> was commanded to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy <hi>Amaleck,</hi> he was charged not only <note place="margin">2. Sam. 15. 3.</note> to kill man, but also sheepe, oxen, and euery liuing thing, man, and beastes, foules, and fishes, trees, and fruites <note place="margin">Zeph. 1. 3. Iere. 7. 20. Ioel. 1. 18.</note> of the earth were punished for mans sinne. And heere wee see, when the sinnes of Israel were red ripe, and the bags of their iniquitie sealed vp, then must the poore harmelesse creatures also smart for it.</p>
            <p>Sinne maketh God to cut downe all: As an earthly King doth not onely
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:20306:78"/> punish a rebell with death, but also ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away his Land; so doth God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so punish man for sinne, in his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities. See how odious sinne is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God; Thou seest pestilence, and plagues among men, so as the very stones in many Cities and Townes, where God hath shot his arrowes for sinne, haue seemed to mourne and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment their solitarinesse, beeing growen ouer with grasse, as the plaine field, knowe it is for thy sinne. Thou seest murraines of Cattle, rots of Sheepe, vnseasonable weather, destroying the Corne, and increase of the earth, thy sinnes are the cause of it. Then mayest thou say with <hi>Dauid, Its I that haue sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Sam. 24. 17.</note>
               <hi>yea I haue done wickedly; but these sheepe what haue they done?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And lastly, whereas the Lord threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, that the Land of <hi>Iudea</hi> should mourne, and all things therein should be destroyed, because <hi>there was no mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, nor truth, nor knowledge of God in the Land: but by swearing, lying, killing, stea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and whoring, they breake out, and blood touched blood.</hi> Let vs looke into our selues, was there euer more want of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:20306:78"/> mercie among the Iewes, then among vs? Is not charity key-cold, and euen frozen amongst vs? Are not swearing, killing, lying, stealing, and whoring too rife? Are not the holy things of the Lord prophaned among vs? Is not the Lords Supper receiued of many without care of examining themselues, or any conscience of making difference of the Lords body? Is not the blessed word, by some made a cloake to couer their sinnes? And, to lap vp all in a word, are not our sinnes ready to pull downe Gods vengeance vppon our heads?</p>
            <p>Let vs then humble our selues by hearty repentance, and breake off the course of sinne betimes, and then God will remooue his iudgements.</p>
            <p>Let vs turne from our sinnes, and <note place="margin">Zach. 1. 3. Ezek. 18. 3. 32.</note> God in mercy will turne to vs. God would not the death of sinners; yea, he expostulateth with vs, or rather wooes vs to himselfe, <hi>Why will ye die, O ye house of Israel?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But except we leaue off sinning, let vs bee sure God will not leaue puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shing: If we continue in sinning, Gods
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:20306:79"/> hand will be still stretched out against vs, and as our sinnes increase, so will he send new iudgements vpon vs. Let vs then make an end of sinning, and God will haue done with afflicting.</p>
            <p>Sinne is like a surfeit, it must needs be remooued, before any medecine can preuaile. <hi>If you amend and redresse your waies, and your workes</hi> (saith the Lord) <hi>then will I let you dwell in this land;</hi> Either <note place="margin">Iere. 7. 5. 7.</note> repent, or no fauour with GOD. Wee must acquaint our selues with GOD, be at peace with him, receaue his words, lay them vp in our hearts, and returne to the Almighty, and then the Lord will deale mercifully <note place="margin">Iob 22. 21. 22, 23.</note> with vs.</p>
            <p>When the weather is vnseasonable, it is a common thing amongst countrey people, to be inquisitiue to know, <hi>When changeth the Moone?</hi> But rather aske, When changest thou thy heart? The right way to appease Gods wrath, is to cast out the <hi>Gibeonites:</hi> and if we would haue Gods wrath turned away, we must <note place="margin">Iudg. 20. 12, 13.</note> cast out our sinnes. Entertaine the counsell of <hi>Daniel, Breake off your sinnes</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4. 24.</note>
               <hi>by righteousnes, and your iniquities by mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi>
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:20306:79"/>
               <hi>towards the poore.</hi> If we doe this, <hi>God will be our Sunne and shield, he will giue vs</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psalm. 84. 9. 11.</note>
               <hi>grace, and glory, he will with-hold no good thing from vs, nor suffer euill things to hurt vs,</hi> and then the controuersie or quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell which the Lord hath with vs (for sinne) will be soone ended. Then will the Lord blesse vs, shew vs the light of his countenance, and be mercifull vnto vs; which God for his mercie sake in Christ Iesus graunt.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
            <closer>Trin-vni Deo glorin.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>